斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到2013至2014秋季学期
Okay, well, welcome then to lecture 10, yes 10,
CS193P第十讲
of CS193P, fall of 2013/14 academic year,
今天我们要讲的是多线程
and today, we are going to talk about multithreading.
我只会简单地讲一下
Okay? I'm only going to talk about it briefly,
因为很多多线程的内容
but, because you'll learn a lot from multithreading
都会通过实际体验学到
kind of through experience.
然后我们会讲UIScrollView滚动视图
Then we're going to talk about UIScrollView,
非常重要的视图
a very important view that allows you
能够扩大手机小屏幕的范围
to expand what you can see on that little phone screen,
让你看到更大的内容
to let you look at larger things.
然后我会做一个示例演示 包含这两项内容
I'll do a demo that's gonna cover both of those things,
多线程和滚动视图
multithreading and scrolling.
然后剩下的时间
And then however much time we'll have left
我们会开始讲下一个主题UITableView表视图
we'll get started on our next topic which is UITableView,
周三再继续
we'll continue that on Wednesday.
先来看多线程
So multithreading, okay.
多线程就是
The idea with multithreading is
将程序的执行路径
that you want to divide up the execution paths of your program
分为不同的路径
into different and distinct paths
可能在同一时间运行
that are possibly running at the same time.
我说"可能" 因为从程序员的角度看
Now I say possibly, from your standpoint as a programmer,
各个线程都是同时运行的
they look like they're all running at the same time.
但是 如果你的电脑或者手机
But, of course, if you have a computer or a phone
只有一个处理器
that only has one processor,
根本不可能同时运行
there's no way for them to run at the same time.
但是操作系统让它们看起来是同时处理的
But the OS makes it appear that they are
方法主要是时间分片
by basically time slicing,
分给每个进程一点时间
giving each one of them a little bit of time
这样看起来它们都是同时运行的
to make it seem like they're all running at the same time, okay?
如果你确实有多个处理器
And, so, if you did have a multiprocessor,
它们可能会同时运行 可能不会
maybe they would actually running at the same time, or maybe not,
但我们不在意也不知道
but you don't care and you don't know.
不是我们要知道的内容
Okay? It's totally not for you to know.
我们为什么需要这种行为呢
Why do we want this kind of behavior
这种多线程执行
where we have these multiple threads of execution?
有一些原因
Well, a couple of reasons.
有一个执行线程
One, we've got one thread of execution
也就是主执行线程
which is that main thread of execution
用户在其中互动 执行触控事件
where the user is interacting, doing touch events,
我们希望它有很好的响应能力
we want thing to be very responsive.
我们想让它始终在监听
We want that to always be listening,
不想让它停止监听
we never want that to not be listening.
另外一个原因就是其他执行线程
The other thing is we have other threads of execution
可能会阻塞
that actually might block, okay?
为什么会阻塞呢
Why would they block?
为什么会停下来
Why would they stop?
比如说执行了一个网络调用
Well, let's say they do a network call
等待返回网络数据
and they're waiting for something to come back over the network.
需要等待返回的内容
Well, they have to wait for that thing to come back.
所以线程会被阻塞 会停住
So they are blocked, they're stopped.
我们不会希望主线程
Okay? We would never want that main execution
监听触控事件的主线程
that's listening for touch events
被停住或被阻塞
to be stopped, okay, or blocked, right?
但是其他线程阻塞就没关系了
But these other ones, it's okay if they're blocked.
如果它们在等待返回数据
If they're waiting for something,
等待就可以了
they're waiting for something. Okay?
想要理解iOS中多线程的实现方法
So to understand how we do multithreading, in iOS,
有一点要理解 也就是queue队列
there's one thing you have to understand and that's queues.
队列和现实世界中的队列是一样的
Okay? A queue, just like a queue in the real world,
队列表示排成一队
queue means like a line,
比如你去电影院 人们会排成一队
like you go to the movie theater and there's a line of people,
这叫做队列
that's called a queue.
向不知道这个词的同学解释一下
For those of you who don't know that word.
如果理解了这个队列的意思
And so you got that queue
iOS多线程这里的队列也是一样的
and the same thing is happening here with iOS multithreading.
这里也有队列 但在这些队列中
You have these queues, but in these queues,
不是等着看电影的人 而是block
instead of people waiting for the theater, there are blocks.
上周我们讲过的block
Blocks in the way we talked about last week.
用大括号表示的block
You know, the curly, curly brace thing, okay?
所以这个队列中都是block
So you got this queue, in line, you have these blocks,
block排着队等着被执行
and they're all waiting in line to be executed.
根据所在队列的不同
And depending on which queue they're in,
当轮到它们 排到了队列前面
when it's their turn, when they get to the front of the line,
它们会被取出队列 开始执行
they get taken off the queue and they get to run.
可能是在单独的线程中
Okay? Possibly in a separate thread.
通常情况下
Okay? Usually there might be
一个队列会分配单个或多个线程
multiple threads assigned to one queue, or single thread,
同样的 你并不知道会怎样
again, you don't know what's going on,
你只知道自己将这些block放入了队列
all you know is you're putting these blocks in a queue
它们会被取出并运行
and they are being taken off and allowed to run.
队列允许一次放一个人
And people can be allowed to come off the queue one at a time,
所以在电影院中
so at the movie theater,
一个人进去看电影
one person gets to go and watch the whole movie,
他看完之后 后面那个人再进去
and when they're done, the next person goes in.
这叫做串行队列
Okay? That's called a serial queue,
这就是我们要讲的队列
that's what the queues we're going to talk about are,
是一个非常简单的队列
it's a very simple queue.
但还有一种并发队列
There's also concurrent queues, however,
可以让一群人进电影院
where a whole bunch of people get to go into a theater
可以同时做某事
and they're all get to be doing stuff simultaneously.
这种略微复杂些
Okay? It's a little more complicated,
因为你得到这个队列 从中取出block
because you got this queue, you're pulling off these blocks
它们一起运行
and they're all running together,
如果它们想要共享资源等等
if they ever want to share resources or something
需要更高级一些的多线程编程
they need a little more advanced multithreaded programming
我们要用的是简单的队列
and we're going to do the simple kind
一次只有一个人从队列中出来
where one person coming out of the queue,
一次只从队列中取出一个block
one block coming out of the queue at the same time.
这就是大家要理解的内容
Okay? So that's really what you understand,
多线程的工作原理就是这样的
is that's how this multithreading works.
由block组成的队列
Queues of blocks, okay?
有一个很重要的队列 就是主队列
Now there's a very important queue, which is the main queue,
在这个队列中处理多点触控
that's the queue on which multi-touch is happening
以及所有UI操作等等
and all the UI stuff is happening,
它很特殊 原因有两点
and this is special for two reasons.
一是我们绝不想让它阻塞
Alright? One is that we never want to block it, okay?
我们不会将需要执行很长时间的线程
So we never want to do anything that's gonna take very long
放在主队列上
on that main queue.
二是我们将其用于同步
And the second thing is we use it for synchronization
所有UI相关内容的同步
for everything that is UI related, okay?
全部方法 也不是全部 UIKit中大部分方法
So all the methods, not all, but most of the methods in UIKit,
只能在主线程中调用它们
you want to call them only on the main queue,
实际上 如果你在其他block中调用它们
and in fact, if you call them on some other, some block
从其他队列中取出的block中 可能不会正常运行的
that came off from some other queue probably wouldn't work.
而有一些对象 比如UIImage UIFont UIColor
Now there's a few, like UIImage, UIFont, UIColor,
它们不在主线程上一样可以正常运行
a couple of those things, they'll work off the main queue,
但任何能够或可能引起
but anything that is going to cause the screen to have to change
屏幕改变或同步等的操作
or synchronize or anything like that, or that might cause that,
都要发生在主队列上
that all needs to happen on the main queue,
所以我们要用主队列
so we use that main queue,
不断响应用户操作
both to have something that's constantly responsive to the user
和进行同步
and for synchronization,
让一切和UI同步
to keep everything in sync of what's going on in the UI side.
其他操作可以放在其他队列中执行
Everything else we could do in other queues,
实际上 令人惊讶的是
and actually, amazingly,
iOS会在其他队列中执行绘制等操作
iOS is doing things like actually drawing in another queue.
你并不知道 不知道是什么队列
Okay, you don't know that, you don't know what queue it is,
你看不到 但实际上是在其他队列中执行的
you don't see it, but it's actually doing the other queue,
为什么呢
why?
因为如果绘制某些复杂图形时
Because if it's drawing something very graphic-intensive
用户在主队列中用了多点触控
and the user multi-touches in the main queue,
就要切换回主队列
you want to switch back to that main queue
赋予优先级
and give it the, the priority
先完成多点触控 绘制稍后执行
and the drawing can wait a little bit while that multi-touch gets done.
所以不要阻塞主队列
Okay? So this main queue doesn't want to be blocked,
我们用主队列来进行同步
it's where we do the synchronization,
我会演示 如何编写代码
and I'm gonna show you how you can write code
让它运行在其他队列中 但还要更新UI
that is running on other queues, but needs to do UI,
因为这是个问题对吧
because that's a problem, right?
如果在其他队列上有block
If your got a block that's on another queue,
不在主队列上
non-main thread queue, non-main queue,
然后还要对UI进行操作
then, and you want to do some UI,
就必须向主队列通信
you got to somehow talk to that main queue,
要在主队列上放一个block
you got put a block, basically, on that main queue.
还有其他队列
There are other queues,
大部分都是iOS在后台创建的
mostly they're created by iOS behind the scenes,
幻灯片中有个示例
I'm going to show you an example here in the slides
会介绍一个API中可以看到的队列
of a queue that is visible to you in the API
以及我们处理的方法
and how we deal with that.
那么如何在其他队列上执行block呢
Alright, so how do you execute a block on another queue?
这是C层API 非常底层的API
Okay? This is a C-level API, it's a very low-level API,
在对象之下 所以在最底这层API中
below object, so you're not going to see any object stuff
不会看到任何对象内容
in this lowest level API.
在这层之上 有一个面向对象层
There is an object-oriented layer on top of it
叫NSOperationQueue
called NSOperation, NSOperationQueue,
但那是内容很少的面向对象层
but it's kind of a thin object-oriented layer.
这是核心层
This is the core layer.
这是最基本的方法
And this is the fundamental method, dis, or, sorry,
基本的C函数 dispatch_async
this is fundamental C function, dispatch, underbar, async,
表示将这个block以异步方式
and that means asynchronously put this block
放入这个队列中
on this queue, okay?
可以看到 我声明了一个队列 局部变量queue
So you see I've declared a queue there, local variable queue,
是dispatch_queue_t类型的 是个typedef
it's a of type dispatch queue t, which is a typedef,
我稍后会介绍如何获取队列
and I'll, I'll talk about how to get a queue in a second.
然后用dispatch_async
And then you just say dispatch async,
然后是目标队列和将要加入队列的block
the queue you want to put the block on and then the block.
block没有参数 无返回值
And the block takes no arguments and it returns no values,
只是一个block 可以随意加入代码
it's just a block, and you can put any code you want in there,
block会在队列中找到位置
and that block will take its place in line on that queue,
队列排到它时 它就会被取出执行
and when that queue gets around it, it will take it off.
关于主队列 还有一件事
One thing, by the way, about the main queue,
它只在安静时才会执行队列中的内容
it never takes anything out of its queue to run until its quiet,
安静指的是当前没有触控事件
meaning whatever current touch events
正在被处理
have been processed, okay?
它不会在处理触控事件时
It's not going to right in the middle of a touch event
从队列中获取某个block
take something off its queue
然后去执行它
and go do something, right?
主队列会等到安静一些时
So the main queue waits till its a little quieter
再从队列中获取操作并执行
and then it'll take things off the queue and run it,
所以你可以向主队列中增加任意操作
so you can always post things on the main queue
肯定不会打断用户操作
and be sure that it's not gonna interrupt the user in anyway.
那么我们如何获取一个队列
Alright, so how do we get a queue to send this,
来执行这个dispatch_async呢
to do this dispatch async with?
先来讲讲如何获取主队列
Well, let's talk about the main queue first
因为要分派操作
because that's the most important queue
它是最重要的队列
that we need to dispatch things,
方法是
and the way you do that
dispatch_get_main_queue
is dispatch underbar get, underbar main, underbar queue,
这个方法会返回主队列
that will return the main queue to you
然后可以对它调用带block参数的dispatch_async
and then you can call dispatch async with a block on that.
在更高的NSOperationQueue层上
At the higher level, that NSOperationQueue level,
可以使用NSOperationQueue mainQueue 它是个类方法
you can do NSOperation mainQueue, it's a class method,
会返回NSOperationQueue对象
it'll return NSOperationQueue object,
代表主队列
which represents the main queue.
它只是内容很少的面向对象层
Again, it's just a thin object-oriented layer,
在C层上
pretty much, on this C layer,
我们会讲到它在API中的使用
and we'll, we'll see where that comes into the API.
如果想要再创建一个队列呢
What if you wanted to create another queue.
假设你要执行大型数学运算
Let's say you're gonna do some big math calculation
或者大型图像处理运算
or some big image processing calculation
而你不想阻塞主队列 主线程
you don't want to block the main queue, the main thread,
这时你就可以再创建一个队列
so you can create another queue.
非常简单 只要用dispatch_queue_create
Very simple, you just say dispatch underbar queue, underbar create,
这个函数的第一个参数是队列的名称
and the first argument to that function is the name of the queue
它会出现在调试程序等之中
and that's like going to show up in the debugger and stuff,
是个内部名称
so this is kind of an internal name,
注意它不是一个NSString
notice that's not an NSString,
因为这是底层API
because this is a low-level API,
这是这门课上
this is about the only non-NSString string
唯一一处使用非NSString字符串的地方
you're ever going to see in this class,
因为这是我们用到的最底层
because this is the lowest level we'll go.
它是个const char
It's a const char star,
这里我就直接用name了
and here I'm just using the name name, okay?
命名时要选择好辨认的名字
You just want to give it a name so you can recognize this queue
方便在调试程序等中认出这个队列
when you see it in the debugger or something like that.
第二个参数代表它是串行队列
And then the second argument is whether it's a serial queue
还是并发队列
or a concurrent queue, right?
NULL代表串行队列
So, NULL means it's a serial queue,
我们要讲的就是这类队列
and so, that's the kind of queue we're gonna talk about,
一次从队列中出来一个人
again, so one person comes out of the line at a time.
对于分派回主队列
And there's kind of an easy mode
有一个简单模式
for dispatching back to the main queue,
就是用performSelectorOnMainThread
which is performSelectorOnMainThread,
它是一个NSObject方法
it's an NSObject method.
可以将它发给任意NSObject
You can send it to any NSObject.
只要直接传递一个selector和它的参数
And you just pass a selector and its argument,
withObject参数 可以为nil
the withObject argument, it could be nil
代表没有参数 是可以的
and then it has no arguments, that's fine.
waitUntilDone代表是否要等待
And the waitUntilDone is whether you're gonna wait
调用它的这个线程执行之后
until this thing gets pulled off the main queue
再将它从主队列调出
and run on the main queue and then finishes
并在主队列上运行
before this thread, that's calling this, goes or not,
waitUntilDone通常设为NO 不需要等待
usually waitUntilDone you would say no, we don't need to wait,
我们会在主队列上调用这个方法
we're going to put this, call this method on the main queue,
轮到它执行时就执行
and whenever it executes is when it executes.
这个performSelectorOnMainThread方法
So, this performSelectorOnMainThread is just
就相当于对主队列调用dispatch_async
like saying dispatch async onto the main queue,
一个调用了该方法的block
a block that just calls that method.
这个方法就是这样
Okay? That's all it is really,
基本上算是个简易模式
bascially it's kind of an easy mode,
看起来很好用
it looks nice, and so, you know,
不用再用dispatch_async方法了
you don't have to do the dispatch async business,
可以直接调用一个方法
but you got to be able to have one method to call,
将所有要执行的操作放到一个方法中
put all the stuff you want to do on one method.
我们看一个使用它的例子
So let's look at an example that uses this, okay?
通过示例演示 更容易理解
This is more understandable, probably much more by example.
这个例子是要下载网上某个URL
So, this example is I want to download the contents of an URL
对应的内容
from somewhere on the internet.
我有一个URL http://或者其他格式
So I have a URL, http:// something or other,
我想要将它从网上下载下来
and I want to download that from the internet.
可能我用的是蜂窝移动网
Well, I might be on cellular,
甚至目前不在网络范围
I might even be out of network range right now,
下载会花费很长时间
that could take a very long time.
可能要几分钟
It could take minutes, okay,
我当然不希望在等待获取URL内容时
well clearly I don't want my user interface, for example,
我的用户界面
to be blocked waiting for the network
被卡主 无法操作
to give me that URL back. Okay?
所以在调用下载操作时
So I have to, basically, call this, do this download,
要将网络下载操作放到另一个队列中执行
network download, in a different queue,
另一个线程 而非主队列
in a different thread, not the main queue. Okay?
iOS中有一个API可以实现这个操作
So there's an API in iOS for doing exactly this,
给它一个URL 它就会在另一个线程中执行
you give it a URL and it will go do it in a different thread.
当它完成时 需要再调用你
Now, when it's done though, it needs to call you back,
告诉你说 我下好这个URL了
and tell you hey, I got that URL,
方法很酷
and the way it does that is kind of cool,
它会将URL内容下载到一个本地文件中
it downloads the URL to a local file,
然后再调用你
and then it calls you back
给你一个本地文件的URL
and gives you a URL to the local file.
这样就变成本地操作了
So now it's all local,
你可以打开文件做各种操作
and so now you can open up the file and do all you want
不会阻塞用户界面操作
and it's not going to be blocking
因为这时不涉及网络因素了
because you, the network is not a part of it anymore,
已经下载好了URL的内容
it's download the contents of the URL.
这是它的具体方法
Okay, so here's how that works.
先创建一个URL请求
First we create a URL request,
URL请求是URL的封装
a URL request is just a wrapper on URL,
是这样创建的
you can see I created there,
requestWithURL:[NSURL urlWithString以及某个URL
requestWithURL, NSURL, object, urlWithString, some URL.
这就是创建URL请求的方法
Okay? So that's how we create a URL request.
URL请求比URL功能更多
A URL request is a little more than URL
你可以为请求指定其他内容
because you can specify some other things about that request,
其他操作
things you want to do,
我们通常会直接创建 就像这里一样
and most of the time we just create it, just like this,
请求没有其他内容了
and we don't do anything else to the request.
现在我们得到了一个URL请求
So now we have a request, a URL, a URL request, and,
抱歉 我发不好URL这个音
I apologize in advance for URL, I have trouble saying that,
后面我要说好多遍
I'm gonna be saying that 100 times in the next few slides.
然后是Configuration配置部分
Then we have this configuration thing,
现在不用担心这部分
don't worry about that for now.
然后创建的是URLSession会话
And then we have, we create what's called a URLSession.
URLSession是一个对象 用来管理一个会话的时间
So URLSession is an object that manages a session of time
开始与网络通信
that goes out and talks to the internet
得到答案等等
and gets the answer and all this stuff,
session会话就是这里要做的主要内容
so the session is the main thing that it's doing here
我们会讲讲创建的方法
and we're going to talk about how we create that,
因为创建NSURLSession的方法
because how we create the NSURLSession determines where,
决定了代码会在哪个线程队列上执行
what thread, which queue, our code is gonna be executed on,
现在我们创建了session 我们可以请求它
and so now we have a session and we can ask the session,
请创建一个任务 下载该URL
please create us a task which downloads that URL,
非常简单 就用downloadTaskWithRequest方法
very simple downloadTaskWithRequest,
给它一个URL请求
you give it the URLRequest,
然后是一个完成处理程序completionHandler
and then you give it a completionHandler.
理解这个completionHandler很重要
Now that completion handler very important to understand,
可以看到 它是一个block 对吧
you can see that it's a block. Right?
block的参数
The arguments to that block,
第一个参数最重要
the first argument is the most important argument,
是本地文件URL
that's the URL of the local file
网络URL的保存地址
that it put the URL into for you.
它将URL内容从网上下载下来
So it downloaded this URL off your internet
保存在本地文件中 再返回文件URL
and it put it in a local file and now it's giving you a file URL,
不是http:// 而是file:文件URL
not an http// URL, but a file, colon, URL, right?
指向本地文件的URL
URL that points to a local file.
还有错误和响应参数
And then the other arguments are about errors and responses,
不用担心
don't worry about those,
主要就是得到这个本地文件
the main thing is you got this local file.
然后 在block中
And then inside this block, okay,
如果要在这里做UI操作呢
what if you wanted to do UI things here? Okay?
如果这个block是在主队列上被执行的
Well, if this block is being executed on the main queue,
你就可以这样做
you're good to go.
但如果是在其他队列上执行的
But if it's being executed on some other queue,
都不能这样做
any other queue, you're not good to go,
需要向主队列通信
you're gonna have to talk back to the main queue.
我们来看一下这两个示例
So let's look at those two examples.
先看一下session会话的创建方法
First of all, let's look at creating the session
用这个方法 sessionWithConfiguration
using this method, sessionWithConfiguration,
这里也不用考虑配置部分
again, don't worry about configuration,
delegate:nil delegateQueue:某个队列
delegate, colon, nil, delegateQueue, colon, some queue.
这个NSURLSession有一个委托
Okay? So this NSURLSession thing, it has a delegate.
还记得委托吗 我们逐渐熟悉了委托
Remember delegates, we're just getting used to delegates now,
希望大家还记得我们用过的动力动画者委托
hopefully you are, remember the dynamic animator delegate that we set
它可以告诉我们动画在何时停止
and it told us when all the animation stopped
然后将方块炸飞
and then we blew up the blocks? Okay?
我们将动画者的一个委托设为控制器
So we just set a delegate of the animator to be the controller
控制器实现方法
and the controller implemented the method.
这里也是一样
Same thing here.
你可以将自己设为这个URLSession的委托
You can set yourself as a delegate to this URLSession,
在进行下载时
and as its doing all its downloading,
它会向你更新状态 我下载了5000字节
it'll give you updates, oh, I loaded it at 5,000 bytes,
又下载了一些 现在下好了文件
I just loaded some more bytes, oh, I've got the file now.
我将它保存在了本地磁盘的一个文件中
Okay, I'm putting it into a file, a local disc,
它会告诉你这些消息
it'll tell you all these things.
你通常不会在意这些内容
Usually you don't care about any of that,
只需要它告诉你什么时候完成了
you just want it to tell you when you're done,
也就是completionHandler的作用
which is what that completion handler is for.
这里我要将委托delegate设为nil
So here I'm going to set my delegate to nil.
我不想得到这些杂乱的消息
I don't even want to hear any of that mess,
我只希望我的完成处理程序
I just want my completion handler
中间的这个 被调用
that you see here, called.
而delegateQueue
But, the delegateQueue, okay,
代表你所有的委托方法
tells you which queue are all your delegate methods
会在哪个队列上被调用
going to be called on, okay?
可以指定为主队列 这里就是
And you can specify the main queue, as we have here,
还可以指定其他队列
or you can specify some other queue.
这里还可以用nil
Okay? You can even pass nil here
它会为你随机分配一个队列
and it'll just make up a queue for you, a random queue.
所以即便这里没有使用委托方法
So even though we're not doing delegate methods here,
也有完成处理程序
we are having that completion handler,
它会在委托的那个队列上
and it calls your completion handler
调用完成处理程序
on the same queue as the delegates.
所以delegateQueue这行代码
So that's why that delegateQueue line there
非常重要
is really important.
这行代码表示调用我的完成处理程序
What that says is call my completion handler,
如果有委托方法 同样调用
and all my delegate methods if I had them,
在这个队列上调用我的完成处理程序
call my completion handler on this queue,
我指定了主队列
and I've specified the main queue.
代表下面这里
So that means the code
completionHandler中的代码
that's inside my completion handler block down there,
黄色部分 写着可以直接做UI操作
the part in yellow that says yes, can do UI things directly,
这段代码会在主队列上被执行
that's being executed on the main queue.
它会被放到主队列的待运行队列上
It gets put in line to run on the main queue,
主队列无操作时
and when the main queue is quiet,
会抓取这段代码并执行它
it'll grab it and execute it.
所以我可以在这里做任意UI操作
So I can do whatever I want UI-wise in here.
因为我在主队列中
I'm on the main queue.
反过来说 不要在这里做开销大的操作
Now, conversely, I wouldn't want to do anything expensive here,
比如查看和解析URL
like, look in the URL and parse it
构建大型数据结构等等
and build some huge data structure and all this stuff,
有可能会阻塞主队列的操作
something that might block the main queue, right?
会花费很长时间
By being, taking a long time.
真的会花费很长时间
I mean, it would have to really take a long time, but, you know,
你肯定不想在那个block中
or you certainly wouldn't want
再增加一个网络调用
to make another network call in that block, okay?
但最重要的是
But, mostly, most importantly,
可以在这里使用UI调用
I can make UI calls here, I could update,
如果这是个图片URL 我可以更新UI显示出来
if this was an image URL, I could update my UI to show the image
或者其他操作
or whatever I want it to do.
因为我已经指定了它会在主队列上执行
Because I've specified that it's gonna run in the main queue.
有问题吗
Okay? Question?
学生提问
Student:[inaudible]
问题是 队列是否会
The question is does a queue finish a block
先完成队列中的一个block
that it takes out of the queue first
然后再抓取下一个
before it grabs another one?
是的 串行队列是这样的
Yes. If it's a serial queue,
我们讲的就是这种队列
which is the kind of queues we're talking about.
会连续地按照顺序执行
Yes. It, it does them in order, serially.
我们来看另一个例子
Okay. So now let's look at a different case.
如果创建NSURLSession时
What if we created NSURLSession
不指定委托队列delegateQueue呢
that does not specify the delegateQueue?
直接用NSURLSession sessionWithConfiguration
So I just use NSURLSession, sessionWithConfiguration,
没有delegat或delegateQueue参数
no delegate, or delegateQueue argument there.
这个例子不用主队列
This case does not use the main queue,
而是另外一个队列
it uses a different queue.
没有委托
Okay? There's no delegate,
所以也不用指定委托方法
so, there's no need to have the delegate method specified.
但回调函数 这个completionHandler
But, the callback, okay, this completion handler
会在另一个队列上执行 而不是主队列
gets executed on a different queue, not on the main queue.
因为我没有指定主队列
Okay? Because I haven't specified the main queue
为其所在执行队列
as the queue I want it to execute on.
所以在这个例子中 如果我要做UI操作
So in this case, if I want to do UI stuff,
需要再增加一个block
I have to make another block of stuff
将其放到主队列上
and put it onto the main queue.
我可以用dispatch_async
And I can do that either with dispatch async,
dispatch_get_main_queue 加一个block
dispatch_get_main_queue, a block,
里面是要做的UI操作
with this stuff, UI stuff I want to do,
或者用self performSelectorOnMainThread
or I could do self performSelectorOnMainThread
加上主队列上的方法
with some method on the main queue,
或者是要执行的方法
or method that I want to execute,
它就会在主队列上被调用
and it'll be called on the main queue.
知道为什么这里我要这样做吗
Okay? So do you see why I had to do that in this case?
因为这个completionHandler
Because this completionHandler
不是在主队列上被调用的
is not being called on the main queue,
是在另外一个队列上
it's being called on a different queue.
这就是iOS中要理解的一点
So this is what, what you need to understand in iOS is,
将block传递给某个方法时
when I have a block that's passed to some method,
要知道它会在哪个队列上被调用
what queue is it going to be called on.
大多数情况下 向iOS方法传递block时
Now most time when you pass a block to an iOS method,
会在调用该方法的那个队列上
it's going to call it on the same queue
调用这个block
that you called that method on.
调用任意方法 给它一个block
Whatever method you called and you handed it a block,
大多数情况下 会在同一个队列上进行回调
it'll call you back on the same queue, most of the time.
但如果是像这里的这个方法一样
But if the method, like this one,
在执行过程中 在其他队列上做了操作
goes off and does something in another queue,
就可能会在另一个队列上进行回调
then it's probably gonna call you back in some other queue,
除非你为其指定了主队列
unless you specify the main queue, okay?
有问题吗
Question?
[学生提问]
[Student: inaudible]
dispatch_async调用是线程安全的吗
Is the call dispatch async thread safe?
是的
And the answer is yes it is.
实际上 你可以将其用于线程同步
And so you can use it for thread synchronization, actually,
因为它是线程安全的
because it is thread safe.
它是原子调用 是原子的
It's an atomic call, okay, it happens atomically.
其他操作出现时
It can't be interrupted
它不会被中断
by something else coming in and doing it.
这是个好问题
So, that's a good question.
大家注意到这个task resume了吗
Notice all, the small thing, you notice I have task resume,
看到这个恢复任务了吗
you see that task resume?
如果用它创建了一个下载任务
When you create a download task using this,
开始时会被挂起 也就是暂停下载
it starts out suspended, in other words, not downloaded.
所以你需要立刻重新开始下载
So you have to immediately resume it to start it, okay?
重新开始操作
Now that resume is going to start something
会在另一个线程执行 而非主队列
happening in a different thread, not on a main thread,
但也要恢复任务
but still, task resume,
不要忘了task resume
don't forget the task resume, okay?
这就是多线程的内容
Okay, that's it for multithreading.
我会在示例中演示
I'm going to do it in the demo,
大家还会再看一遍
so you'll get another look at it.
大家要在作业中实现这部分
You'll be doing it in your homework
所以你们会熟悉它的
so you'll get a feel for it.
主要就是要理解这个思路
The idea here is to get this idea,
主队列和其他队列
this main queue and these other queues,
在其他队列中做任何操作时
and that I have to post back to the main queue
都要向主队列回传消息
anytime I'm doing something on another queue.
然后是UIScrollView滚动视图
Okay. UIScrollView.
UIScrollView是一个很重要的视图
So UIScrollView is a really important view.
iPhone屏幕很小
You know, the iPhone screen,
任何能装进口袋的设备
anything that's going to fit in your pocket
屏幕都很小
is going to have a small screen,
但你可能想用它
but you might want to have it
看很多信息
looking at a lot of information, okay?
希望能够轻松导航至所需位置
And you want to easily navigate through that.
这里有一小段视频
Now I have this little video here,
好像是iOS4的
this is like from iOS 4, or something,
所以这里...
that's why I left it with the...
所以用的是旧款iPhone的背景
or it has the old background, the old kind of phone,
但它能很好地展示滚动视图的作用
but it's really good at showing what scroll view can do,
滚动视图中可以添加任意视图
because you can put any kind of view in a scroll view,
包括另一个滚动视图
including another scroll view.
可以看到这里的滚动视图
So you can see that I've got a scroll view
是水平滚动的
that's scrolling horizontally,
而其中内容是垂直滚动的
and the things in it are scrolling vertically.
这是一个股票应用
Okay? Or here's a stock app
多个滚动视图
where I'm going scrolling horizontally
可以水平滚动
through other scroll views
而每个视图内部可以垂直滚动
that can scroll vertically inside of them.
看到了吗
You see that?
所以这里可以显示出很多信息
So I can present a lot of information here,
不只有股票报价
not just the stock ticker value,
还有某只股票的新闻 图表等等
but news about a stock, charts, etc.,
通过滚动可以轻松获取
and I can just easily get at them by scrolling through.
滚动视图是一个非常强大的设计视图
So scroll view is a really powerfully designed view
可以在滚动区域放几乎任何对象
that lets you put almost anything in the area it scrolls,
包括其他滚动视图
including other scroll views.
我们来看一下滚动视图的用法
Okay? So, let's look at how scroll view works.
可以为滚动视图添加子视图
Scroll view is really just a view that you add subviews to,
但它会特别处理这些子视图
but it treats those subviews specially,
因为它允许你对其进行滚动和缩放
because it lets you scroll around them and zoom in on them.
大家知道如何向普通UIView添加子视图吧
So you know how to add a subview to a normal UIView, right?
只要设好子视图的frame 调用addSubview
You just set the frame to subview, you call addSubview,
它就会显示在视图中了 很简单
bloop, it appears in the view, easy.
即使你对一个很大的视图使用addSubview
Even if you have a huge view and you say addSubview,
它会添加这个子视图
somewhere down there, oop, it gets added,
但是当然了 你没有办法看到整个视图
but, of course, you can't see the whole view.
你可以缩小它
Now you could shrink the view way down small,
但那样就会像这幅斯坦福的图片一样
but then, like this Stanford picture,
几乎什么都看不清楚
you'd hardly even be able to see anything. Okay?
所以这里我们真正想要做的是
So really what we want to do
滚动查看它们
is be able to scroll around on these things.
如何向UIScrollView添加子视图呢
So, how does this work adding subviews to UIScrollView?
有一点很重要
Well, there's one really important thing,
这是UIScrollview的要点
this is the take-home point on UIScrollview.
要设置它的contentSize
You got to set its contentSize.
它有一个属性叫做contentSize
So it has a property, called contentSize,
尺寸很大
which is just a big size, and it makes the area
它代表滚动视图要滚动的区域
that the scroll view is going to scroll around on.
我设置了一个很大的contentSize 3000*2000
Okay? This, I made a big contentSize here, 3,000 by 2,000.
现在再向滚动视图添加子视图时
Then, now when you add subview to the scroll view,
它会将它放入其内容区域中
it puts it in its content area, essentially.
这里我添加了subview1 是斯坦福的标志
So here I put this subview1, which is the Stanford logo,
向右2700 向下100 看到了吗
2,700 across, 100 hundred down, you see that?
再将那个大的子视图放进去
And then let's put that big one in there, somewhere.
放到50,100的位置上
Okay, I put it 50 by 100 in there.
这时滚动视图要做的是
And now what the scroll view is going to do
为内容区域提供一个窗口
is really kind of provide a window on that content area.
随着用户用手指来回滚动
So as the user scrolls around, with their finger,
它就会随着移动
it's essentially going to move around
显示出内容区域的内容
showing you what's in that content area, alright?
明白吗
Does that make sense?
滚动视图就是这样的
So that's all scrolling is, really,
对它进行拖动时就是这样的
when it comes to the panning part of it.
这些视图的位置可以随意更改
And you can position these views anywhere you want,
所以如果我将斯坦福标志移到这里
so if I move this Stanford logo here
将大的子视图移到左上角
and then I move that huge thing to the upper corner,
将contentSize缩小一点
maybe I change my contentSize to be smaller,
包含两个子视图
to include the views, okay,
现在依旧可以来回滚动
now, again, I can scroll around,
可以看到各部分 这里是斯坦福标志
and you can see various parts, there's that Stanford logo,
它与下面的视图重叠了
it's kind of overlapping the, the view here,
因为这两个视图与内容区域重叠了
because those two views overlapping the content area, etc.
就是这么简单
So it's as simple as that.
只要设置好contentSize
It's all about that contentSize thing.
作为程序员 你可能想要知道
Now, as a programmer, you might want to know
用户当前所视位置
where is the current, the user currently looking,
是内容区域的哪部分
okay, in my content area.
可以通过滚动视图的一个属性得到
And the way to get that is the scroll view property
contentOffset
contentOffset.
它可以告诉你当前显示区域
It tells you the X and Y of the upper left corner
左上角的X和Y的坐标
of the area that's being viewed.
这是很重要的一部分
Okay? So that's an important part of it.
另外一项你要知道的内容是
The other thing you want to know is
用户所示区域的边界bounds
what's the bounds of the area the user is looking at,
这部分有点...
and somewhat,
有些人在理解这部分时遇到了困难
some people had a little trouble understanding this,
但其实很简单
but it's very simple,
就是滚动视图的边界
that bounds is actually just the scroll views bounds.
滚动视图是个视图
Okay? The scroll view is a view,
它有边界 self.bounds
it has bounds, self dot bounds,
它的边界就是用户所视区域的范围
and that bounds is the area that's being looked at.
这个边界是在内容区域的坐标系中的
Now that bounds is in the content areas coordinate system,
你可能不想要它 你想要知道的是
okay, and you may not want that, you might want to know
图像中哪部分是当前显示出来的
in that image what is being looked at.
要实现它 只要转换坐标
And to do that, you simply convert those coordinates
用这个视图方法convertRect toView
using this view method, convertRect toView.
得到滚动视图的边界 使用convertRect toView
So you take those scroll view bounds, you convertRect toView,
后面是其子视图
whatever subview in there,
比如当前显示
like the UIImageView that's displaying,
斯坦福图片的这个UIImageView
displaying that Stanford picture,
这样你就可以知道
and you can find out where...
在视图坐标系中的范围
what it is in that view's coordinate system.
为什么会不一样呢
Now why would those be different?
这里的斯坦福图片
Well, okay, that Stanford thing happens to be
正好在左上角(0,0)的位置
up in the upper left corner at 0, 0,
所以看起来是一样的
so it looks like it would be the same,
如果不是在(0,0)的位置 就要区别了
but if that were not at 0, 0, then that would matter.
而且它还可以被缩放
Also it could be zoomed.
我们稍后会讲缩放部分
We'll talk about zooming in a second,
因为滚动视图也可以被放大
because scroll views can also zoom in,
假设你把它放大了
and so if you imagined if you were zoomed way in,
放大显示一扇窗户
looking in a window there,
斯坦福图片视图中的矩形区域
that the rectangle inside the Stanford view's view
会是一个很小的矩形
would be a very small rectangle, right,
而在滚动视图中会包含很大范围
where as in scroll view it's containing huge amounts.
所以这二者
So that's why it makes a difference
是有区别的
what those two things are.
我们来讲一下如何创建滚动视图
Okay? So let's talk about how you create a scroll view.
非常简单
Very easy.
直接从storyboard中拖出就可以了
You just drag it out from your storyboard.
这是创建滚动视图的首选方法
Okay? That's the number one way to create scroll view,
还可以用alloc initWithFrame
you can also do alloc initWithFrame,
它也只是个视图 和其他视图一样
it's just a view like any other view,
但通常会直接拖出来
but usually you drag it out.
如果storyboard中有一个视图
It is possible to have a view sitting in your storyboard
还可以选择编辑菜单中的嵌入滚动视图
and do edit menu, embed in scroll view,
和嵌入导航控制器类似
just like you do embed in navigation controller.
也许是我没理解
You know, maybe I don't understand exactly
它究竟应该是怎样的
how that's supposed to work,
但就我看来
but it seems to me like
很多情况下都会出问题
it doesn't do the right thing a lot of the time.
比如说
For example,
它会在周围留出额外的空间
it seems to put like a little extra space around it,
我也不知道原因 我不推荐使用嵌入滚动视图
I'm not sure, I don't recommend embed in scroll view.
我推荐添加好滚动视图之后
I recommend just put your scroll view there
然后用代码增加子视图
and then add your subviews in code, okay?
或者将它们拖入storyboard中的滚动视图中
Or, drag them in to a scroll view that's in your storyboard
将它们放到那里
to put them in there, okay?
但是子视图直接拖拽进滚动视图有点奇怪
But dragging them into your scroll view it kind of weird,
因为storyboard中的滚动视图
because your scroll view in the storyboard
只能显示出其可视区域
can only show you its visible area,
不能将整个contentSize的内容显示出来
it can't show you that huge contentSize.
所以我更倾向于用代码
So I'm kind of a fan of
添加滚动视图的子视图
put your scroll view's subviews in code.
添加滚动视图时
Okay? You put the scroll view itself in,
可以在storyboard中使用拖放完成
drag and drop, into your storyboard,
然后用代码添加子视图
but then, put your things in code,
我推荐这种方法
I kind of recommend that.
实现方法就是使用addSubview方法
And the way you do that is just with addSubview.
只要设置好视图的frame
Just set the frame you want for your view,
是在内容区域的坐标系中的
which is in that content area, coordinate system,
然后用addSubview
and there's addSubview.
就是这么简单
Simple as that.
不要忘记设置contentSize
Don't forget to set that contentSize.
这是我讲的第一项内容
That's the very first thing I talked about
我要再强调一遍
and I'm talking about it again.
如果不设置contentSize 就是那个大的白色区域
If you don't set that contentSize, that big white area,
滚动视图就没有滚动显示内容了
the scroll view is going to be scrolling over nothing.
无论子视图添加的是哪个视图
It doesn't matter what views you've added a subview,
contentSize是它滚动显示的对象
that contentSize is what it scrolls over.
并不是在视图上滚动
It doesn't scroll over the views,
视图只是正好在那里
the views just happen to be there
如果它们是在contentSize坐标系中的话
if they're in the contentSize coordinate system,
contentSize才是关键
but it's that contentSize that's key,
不要忘了设置它
don't forget to set that.
要想重置它
And to reset it,
如果滚动显示的对象大小发生变化
if you're gonna scroll over something that changes size,
放大缩小等等
it gets larger or smaller or whatever,
重置那个contentSize
reset that contentSize.
大多数情况下
Most of the scrolling around
滚动操作是由用户的拖动手势控制的
is the user with a touch gesture panning,
但还可以用代码完成滚动
but you can also scroll around using code.
比如scrollRectToVisible
For example, scrollRectToVisible.
你在内容区域指定一个矩形
You specify a rectangle in the content area,
它会滚动以显示那个矩形
and it will scroll that to make that rectangle visible,
也许要为其添加动画 让它划过去
and you probably want it to be animated so it slides over,
而不是突然蹦出来
instead of just jumps, right?
对于滚动视图
And there's a ton of other things
还可以控制很多其他操作
you can control in a scroll view,
我们就不讲了
which we're not going to talk about,
时间有限
just time constraints,
大家可以回去查看UIScrollView的文档
but you can go look at UIScrollView's documentation,
比如滚动在何时启用
things like whether scrolling is enabled at a given time,
是水平滚动还是垂直滚动 还是二者兼有
whether you can scroll horizontally or vertically or both,
iOS中没有滚动条
there's no scroll bars in iOS,
但有滚动指示器
but there are scroll indicators,
不用滚动条
you don't use scroll bars,
因为是直接用手指滚动
because you just scroll with your finger,
或者是用拖动触控手势
or you pan around with a touch gesture,
但会出现小标志
but there are little things that flash on
告诉你当前所在内容区域的位置
that kind of show you where you are on the content area,
这些内容都可以在文档中找到
you can look at all that stuff in the documentation.
现在我们来讲一下缩放
Alright, so now let's talk about zooming.
我们讲过了在滚动视图上拖动
Okay, so we've talked about panning around the scroll view,
如果想要对内容进行缩放呢
what if we want to zoom in on the content and zoom out?
要记得 所有UIView都有transform变换属性
Remember that all UIViews have this transform property.
在动画部分 我们将其用于了评分效果
Okay? We used it to grade effect in the animating world,
变换可以对视图进行任意的
and the transform let's you rotate and scale
旋转 缩放和平移
and translate a view, arbitrarily, okay,
是基于比特位的缩放
it's doing bits, though, bit-wise zooming,
UIScrollView利用它
and UIScrollView takes advantage of that
实现缩放
to do its view, do its zooming
方法是通过修改变换属性的缩放比例
by changing the scale of the transform.
按缩放比例进行变换
Okay? So it scales the transform.
也就意味着你的视图
So that means that your view,
如果放大太多 可能会看不清楚
if it's zoomed in a lot could be kind of greeny,
除非你的视图
unless your view doesn't know
不知道在缩放时如何进行调整
how to adjust itself once it's zoomed in,
我们稍后会讲
and we'll talk about that in a second.
要实现缩放 要设置两项重要的内容
Zooming requires two very important things to be set,
首先是最大最小缩放比例
the first thing is the minimum and maximum zoom scale,
它们的默认值是1
by default these are one,
代表无法进行缩放
meaning you can't zoom in or out.
显示的缩放比例为1
Okay? It's just gonna show you a zoom scale of one,
也就是说 用户看到的内容
in other words, the thing the user sees is one times the size
是它的实际大小
of the thing as it really, it's actual size, right?
所以如果你想要让它们实现缩放
So, if you want them to be able to zoom in or zoom out,
就要设置最大最小缩放比例
you have to set the minimum or maximum zoom scale.
否则无法进行缩放
Okay? Otherwise you will not zoom.
第二项是一个委托方法
The second thing is a delegate method.
缩放的滚动视图要有一个委托
So, scroll views that zoom have to have a delegate.
委托只是滚动视图的一个属性
Okay? And delegate is just a property, on scroll view,
和动画部分类似
just like it was on the animator,
你要将委托设为某个对象
you're gonna set that delegate to be some object,
通常是你的控制器
usually your controller,
控制器会实现所需要的
and your controller's gonna implement whatever methods
UIScrollView委托协议中的方法
in the UIScrollView delegate protocol,
我们讲过 记得吧
remember we talked about protocols that it wants.
UIScrollView委托中的方法都是可选的
All the methods in the UIScrollView protocol are optional,
但如果想实现缩放 这个方法是必须的
but this one is not optional if you want zooming,
这个方法viewForZoomingInScrollView
and all of this method, viewForZoomingInScrollView
会返回在内容区域中
is returning is which view, in the content area,
滚动视图的哪个子视图
which subview of the scroll view,
会在缩放时改变缩放比例
is going to have it scale changed when it zooms?
所以在滚动视图的内容区域内
Okay? So you might have a view at the top level
你可能会有一个顶级视图
inside your content area scroll view
包含所有要缩放的视图
that contains all your other views and they're zooming in,
没问题
that's fine,
或者只有一个可以缩放的视图
or there might be just one view that makes sense to zoom,
但是需要返回
but you have to return
哪个子视图会被按比例缩放
which subview is going to get scaled,
变换要应用于哪个视图
which it's gonna have this transform applied to it.
还可以编程实现缩放
Okay? You can also zoom programmatically, again,
用户通常会通过捏放手势控制缩放
the user is usually pinching to zoom,
但也可以用编程实现
but you can do it programmatically
只要设置这个属性zoomScale
by just setting this property zoomScale.
设置时可能要使用
When you do set it, you probably want to set it
setZoomScale animated
with setZoomScale animated,
而不是直接设置zoomScale属性
instead of just setting the zoomScale property directly
这样就有动画效果了
so that it gets animated.
还可以按矩形缩放
And you can also zoom to a rectangle,
是这样的
which looks like this,
这是缩放比例1.2的显示效果
so here's zoom scale 1.2,
将它放大了一点
so I'm zoomed in a little bit.
如果将缩放比例设为1 就是实际大小
If I got to zoom scale 1, okay, this actual size,
可以再回到缩放比例1.2
I can go back to zoom scale 1.2.
还可以按矩形缩放
I can also zoom to a rectangle,
比如说 这里有个小矩形
let's say I have this little rectangle right here,
这个兽像的鼻子
this nose of this beast,
如果对它进行放大 会尽可能放大
and if I zoom, it will make it as big as possible, okay?
还能放下 所以就放大了
It still fits, so it zooms in.
如果这个矩形
Or, if I had a square that was bigger
大于当前显示范围
than what was currently showing
这时再用zoomToRect 它就会缩小
and I said zoomToRect, it'll zoom it down.
所以你可以直接用矩形
Okay? So you can basically just take a rectangle
让它缩放到合适大小
to make it fit as best it can. Alright.
滚动视图有很多委托方法
So scroll view has lots and lots of delegate methods
不只是有viewForZoomingInScrollView
besides that viewForZoomingInScrollView thing.
例如 如果捏合放大
For example, if you zoomed in, you pinched to zoom
将一个视图放大很多
and you zoomed way in on a view,
会变得很像素化
it's gonna be really pixelated
因为是按比例变换大小
because it's gonna be doing a transformed-based scale, right?
将比特位按比例放大 可能会变得很大
Scaling the bits up, bits might look huge,
但是有一个委托方法
but you get a delegate method,
scrollViewDidEndZooming withView atScale
scrollViewDidEndZooming withView atScale,
滚动视图会告诉你
that will tell you, the scroll view will tell you,
我完成它的缩放操作了
I just finished zooming this thing
它现在是预设缩放比例
and now it's at this scale.
这时你就可以重绘视图 让它不再像素化
And now you could redraw your view to not be pixelated.
这是个好方法
Okay? So this would be a good way
用户可以随意缩放
to kind of let them zoom in and out,
性能很高 略有像素化
really high performance, a little pixelated,
但用户的手指还在上面
but their fingers are in the way anyway,
所以他们可能不太察觉
so they can't probably can't tell that much.
当用户移开手指时 你就可以重绘了
And then when they let go, you can do it.
实际上 在执行时你会得到通知
And in fact, you even get notification while it's doing it,
所以可以在执行时进行重绘
so you could even do it while it's doing it,
最好用性能较高的绘制操作
it better be a high-performance drawing
因为同时还要处理捏合操作
because they're pinching in and out.
但是这样做是可以的
But, you could do it.
我只想演示一个委托方法
But I just wanted to show you an example of a delegate method.
可能还有十几个滚动视图委托方法
There's probably a dozen more scroll view delegate methods,
大家可以查看UIScrollView委托文档
you could go look at the UIScrollView delegate documentation
查看这些方法
to find out what they are all.
明白了吗
Okay?
我们来做个演示
So, we'll do a demo.
演示包含很多内容
It's a pretty comprehensive demo.
我要演示滚动视图的操作
I'm gonna be doing, showing you scroll view,
以及URL下载
and that URL downloading thing,
还要演示
and I'm also going to show you,
再做一个导航控制器
we'll do another navigation controller,
再在课堂上演示一遍
just to show it again in class.
最后我要演示一点动画的内容
And at the end, I'm gonna show you a little animation thing,
是一个转轮
a spinner that can spin
会在其他线程执行操作时旋转
while things are happening in other threads,
主线程显示这个小转轮
so the main thread can show his little spinner
用户就能知道是怎么回事了
so people can see what's going on.
争取在下课前都演示完
So, we'll try to get all of that to fit into our time.
这里新建一个项目
So we're gonna make a new project here.
选择新建项目
So I'm just gonna create new project.
我要叫这个项目Imaginarium
And I'm gonna call this project Imaginarium.
将Imaginarium保存在根目录Developer下
Okay? Imaginarium, we'll put it in my home directory developer,
强烈推荐这样
which I highly recommend.
出来了
Here it is.
我要将AppDelegate拖入Supporting Files文件夹中
Okay, I'm dragging AppDelegate to supporting files.
下下周
Probably the week after next
我们可能会讲这个应用委托
we'll start talking about this app delegate.
讲到iOS的多任务处理时
Really the app delegate mostly comes in
通常会涉及应用委托
when we talk about multitasking in iOS,
多任务处理部分
and we will start talking about multitasking
会在下下周讲到 今天不会涉及
the week after next, but not today.
我们就用这个基本的视图控制器
So here we go with this basic view controller, right here,
这个空的视图控制器
this blank view controller.
我只要新建一个MVC
And I'm gonna start off right off the bat by making a new MVC,
一个新的视图控制器 它的作用是
a new view controller, and what this view controller does is
获取一个URL 然后显示出来
it takes a URL, and displays,
URL对应的是网络上某幅图像 某个jpeg文件
that is a URL that's for an image on the internet, some jpeg file,
把它显示出来
and it displays it.
这就是要做的操作
Okay? So that's what this,
先要创建它
this first thing I'm going to create is.
直接选择新建文件
So let's just go straight to that, new file,
新建一个类
I'm gonna create a new class,
是一个UIViewController
it's gonna be a UIViewController, okay,
我要叫它ImageViewController
I'm gonna call it ImageViewController.
因为这就是它的作用
Okay? Because that's what it does,
显示图像的视图控制器
the view controller displays an image.
保存在这里
Put it right there.
这就是我的ImageViewController
So here's my ImageViewController,
从这个公有API入手
I'm going to start right with this public API,
要对新类进行操作
as I want to do with new classes,
我要增加一个属性
so, I'm going to have a property,
是nonatomic strong类型 是一个NSURL
which is nonatomic strong, which is going to be an NSURL,
叫做imageURL
which is imageURL, okay?
这是公有API
So this is the public API.
如果你设置了这个imageURL
If you set this imageURL,
这个视图控制器就会显示那幅图像
this view controller will display that image.
要怎么做呢
Okay? How's it going to do that?
会用到一个类
It's going to use a class,
我们几周前讲过 叫做UIImageView
which we talked about a few weeks ago, called UIImageView.
就像UILabel是显示文本的一样
UIImageView is kind of like UILabel is to text,
UIImageView是显示图像的
UIImageView is to image.
它会获取一个UIImage 它有个属性是UIImage
It just takes a UIImage, it has a property which is a UIImage,
然后显示它 这就是我们想要的功能
and it displays it, so it's exactly what we want.
这个控制器显然要用到它
So this controller is obviously going to use that,
删掉这些内容
so let's get rid of all this stuff, and,
想要实现这个操作 这里需要什么呢
so what do I need here, to do this?
需要一个图像视图
Well, I'm gonna need one of those image views.
创建一个UIImageView
So let's create a UIImageView, okay?
为什么不对呢
Alright, why is that not doing the right thing already?
好吧
Okay.
我们看看
Let's see there.
可能是因为这个
Oh, maybe because this.
不管了
But anyway.
我们创建好了这个imageView
Okay, sorry, we have this imageView,
它是主要内容
that's gonna be the main thing,
对它进行延迟实例化
so I'm going to lazily instantiate that.
(UIImageView *)imageView
Image view, imageView,
if(!_imageView) _imageView=[[UIImageView alloc] init]
if not imageView then imageView equals UIImageView alloc,
这时候我不知道它的框架是什么
and at this time, I don't know its frame,
我就将它设为(0,0)了
so I'll just make it be (0,0),
但要确保框架被正确设置
but I'll have to make sure its frame gets set properly,
在某个时刻 设置图像时
at some point, when I set its image
最好确保框架设置正确
I better to make sure its frame is set properly.
就是这样了
And, so we have that,
这里我要再做一个有趣的操作
now I'm gonna do another interesting thing while we're here,
演示一下是如何实现的
just to show you how this is done.
我要再添加一个属性
I'm gonna have another property,
是一个UIImage
which is going to be a UIImage.
它就是我们要显示的图像
And this is going to be the image we're displaying,
关于这个属性有趣的一点是
but what's interesting about this property,
我不会用一个实例变量来储存它
is I'm not gonna use an instance variable to store it.
我会实现setter和getter
Okay? I'm going to implement the setter and the getter,
但不会用实例变量
and I'm not going to use an instance variable.
怎样实现呢
Okay? So how does that work?
我们来实现getter
Well, let's do the getter.
是image
Oops. Image.
这样做时
And when I do this,
只要返回imageView的视图
I'm just gonna return my imageView's view,
imageView的image
image, rather, my imageView's image.
有对象想要这个属性时
Okay? So when someone wants this property,
它是个私有属性
it's a private property,
我在代码中想要这个属性时
but whenever I want this property in my code,
只要返回imageView的image
I'm just going to return the imageView's one,
设置image也类似
and, similarly, when I set this image, okay,
看看能不能让它
let's see if we can make this do the right thing
显示正确的代码颜色
in terms of code coloring,
我也不确定是怎么回事
I'm not sure what's going on here.
再打开一遍试试
Let's try this again.
我也不知道
Okay, I'm not exactly sure.
好了
Oh, there we go.
我想让这些代码颜色显示出来
Okay, I want to get this colors going here.
好了 我们来设置UIImage
Alright, so, let's set our UIImage.
这里也是一样的 只要用
And same thing here, I'm going to just
self.imageView.image=image
self dot imageView, dot image, equals the image.
为什么要定义这个image属性呢
But here's why I'm defining this little image,
因为每次设置imageView的image时
because whenever I set the image in the imageView,
都需要做另外一个操作
I need to do one other thing,
self.imageView sizeToFit
which is self dot imageView sizeToFit.
我想让imageView
Okay? I want the imageView
调整自身框架 以适应图像显示
to adjust its frame to fit that image.
因为每次设置imageView的image时
So, since I always want to do that
都要这样做
whenever I set the imageView's image,
我只要准备一个自己的属性
I'm just preparing my own little property,
具有合理的语义
which has sensible semantics,
通过它来做这个sizeToFit
that does this little sizeToFit.
设置图像时要做的其他操作
There are some other things we're going to want to do
可以都放到这里
when we set an image, and we can put them all in here,
我们这里就先这样了
but we'll start with just these. Okay?
下面要做的是在viewDidLoad中...
The next thing I need to do is, in viewDidLoad...
像这样
Like this.
将这个imageView加到self.view中
Let's go and add this imageView to self dot view.
super viewDidLoad 然后是
So let's do super, viewDidLoad, and then I'm going
self.view addSubview:self.imageView
to say self dot view, addSubview, self dot imageView.
这样让它显示在屏幕上
Okay? So that way I make sure I get it on screen.
有问题吗
Question?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
非常棒的问题
Yeah. Great, great question.
这里没有@synthesize
So, there's no at sign synthesize for UI...
UIImage这里没有 对吗
this UIImage thing, right?
编译器也没有提示错误
And compilers not complaining either.
怎么回事
What is going on?
为什么不需要@synthesize呢
Why don't I need an at sign synthesize?
有人想猜一把吗
Anyone want to hazard a guess?
[学生回答]
Student:[inaudible]
没错
Correct.
答案就是因为我不用实例变量
The answer is because I never use the instance variable.
因为image完全是按照另一个对象
Okay? Since image is totally defined
来定义的
in terms of another object,
我绝不会用_image
I'm never using underbar image,
所以我不用合成那个实例变量
and therefore I don't need to synthesize that instance variable,
@synthesize就是这个功能
that's what at sign synthesize does.
它用来创建实例变量 而我不需要
It creates that instance variable, and I don't need it.
编译器没有报错
So, the compiler's not complaining
是因为我没有用它 所以不需要
because I'm not using it, so I don't even need it.
这就是为什么我用了这个属性
Everyone, that's kind of why I did this property,
给大家演示一下
so that you would see that.
大家都明白了吗
Okay? Everybody got that?
现在有了这个很棒的视图
Okay, so now I have this wonderful view.
这里要做的最后一件事是
The last thing I want to do here is
当有人设置我的公有API 设置imageURL时
when someone sets my public API, set imageURL,
显然我要将imageView的image设成它
obviously, I want to set that imageView's image to be that,
在这里存储imageURL
so let's store our imageURL here,
然后是 self.image=
and then I'm just gonna say self dot image equals NS...
[UIImage imageWithData:[NSData
sorry, UIImage, imageWithData, NSData,
dataWithContentsOfURL self.imageURL]]
dataWithContentsOfURL, self dot imageURL.
扩大点显示空间
Okay? Let's make some more space. Okay?
这里做的就是调用这个self.image
So, all I'm doing here is I'm calling this self dot image,
它会调用下面的这个setImage方法
which is going to call this down here, this setImage.
使用获取的数据新建UIImage
And, I'm creating a new UIImage using the data
数据就是URL的内容
that I get by getting the contents of that URL.
这会阻塞线程
This is going to block,
因为这个URL是互联网上的
because that URL is gonna be out on the internet.
如果这个URL是网上的 这里就会阻塞
If that, if this URL is on the internet, this will block.
如果是文件URL就不会 会直接获取数据
If it's a file URL it won't, it'll just get the data.
但理解这部分很重要
Okay? But this is very important to understand.
这里可能会阻塞主队列
This is where we might be blocking the main queue.
那样就不好了
Okay? And that's gonna be bad.
我们会阻塞主队列
We're going to block the main queue
然后我们会再开启它
and then we're going unblock it, okay?
但开始会阻塞它 这很不好
But we're gonna start out blocking out, which is bad,
这行代码会带来麻烦
but this is the line of code, the offender,
因为dataWithContentsOfURL会涉及网络
because dataWithContentsOfURL will go out on the network
如果这个URL是http开头的话
if that URL is an http something. Okay?
我们要显示什么图像呢
Okay, so, now what image are we going to display?
我们写好了这个好用的通用图像显示器
Right? We have this nice, generic image displayer,
我们要显示什么呢
what are we going to display?
上一下网
And, now let's go in the internet.
这些图像是苹果公司网站上的
So, I've got these images right here, that actually Apple has,
苹果公司在网站上放了一些示例图片
they put up a few images that were kind of example images
iPhone的拍摄样张 我猜是iPhone5s
that were taken by an iPhone, iPhone5s, I guess,
可以看到 这幅图叫photo_1
and you can see there's this one, photo one,
是朵花 再看一下photo_2
which is this flower and then there's photo two,
应该是小辣椒
which is these peppers, I guess those are,
photo_3是水母
and three, which is this jellyfish, okay?
我想让我的应用能够显示这些图像
So I want to have my app be able to display these images.
我要让应用
Okay? So I'm going to make it
能够显示这三幅图中任意一幅
so it can display any of these three images.
要怎么实现呢
So how am I going to do that?
回到storyboard中
Alright, I'm gonna go to my storyboard,
首先拖出一个视图控制器
and first I'm gonna drag out a view controller
作为我的图像视图控制器
to be my image view controller,
将它拖出来
so let's drag that out,
大家都知道 需要将它的类
and we know that we need to set its class
设为ImageViewController
to be ImageViewController,
现在就有了这个图像视图控制器
so now I have this nice image view controller
用来显示图像
that can display an image.
现在我要在这个视图控制器中加些按钮
And, now I'm gonna put some buttons in this view controller,
这是创建应用时
this is this default view controller
自动创建的默认视图控制器
that got created when I created the app,
在这里添加一个按钮
so I'm going to create one here.
一个按钮用来显示小辣椒
We'll create one for the peppers,
或者是其他东西
and... or whatever those things are,
再添加一个按钮
and then let's create one for the...
显示第一幅图的花 然后
what was the first one, a flower, and then,
最后一个是水母
what was the other thing, it was a jellyfish.
添加好这些按钮后 我希望...
Okay, so I got these buttons and I want to...
当我点击这些按钮时
when I click on these buttons,
对应的图像会显示在这边
I want it to show up here, okay?
我要通过导航控制器来实现
So, I'm gonna use that by doing a navigation controller
让它进行segue
and have it segue, okay?
这样我们可以再复习一遍segue
Just so we can review the segues.
这三个按钮还要一起调整一下
One thing I want to do all of these is,
让它们对齐
let's give them some nice things here.
让它们水平居中
Let's have them, horizontally center that way,
让它居中
let's have this guy horizontally centered...
这样垂直居中
vertically centered this way.
从第二个control拖拽到第一个按钮
Let's control, drag from this guy up this
让它们保持垂直间距
and keep the vertical spacing,
control拖拽到第三个按钮 设置保持垂直距离
control, drag this into that vertical space,
都做完之后
so I do all that,
可以看到出现了黄线
you can see I have some yellow here,
黄色的约束线 我们把它改好
some yellow constraints, let's go fix those.
转到左边 点击黄色三角形
We'll go over here, do this,
点击修复错位按钮
we'll fix the misplacement there.
改好这里 以及这里
And fix that one, and we'll fix that one.
这样就好了
So now they're doing it.
这里正好可以转到右上 选择这项
This might be a nice chance to go here and select on this
切换到横屏模式
and go switch over to landscape.
看起来效果不错
It looks like it's doing something sensible,
很好
so that's good.
大家明白了吗
Okay? Everybody got that?
复习一下自动布局的内容
Just a little review of autolayout there.
我们将它
Alright, so, let's put this inside
放入导航控制器中
of a navigation controller,
选择嵌入导航控制器
so I'm gonna embed in navigation controller,
将它放在了这里
so that puts that here.
很好
That's good.
我们在这里加一个标题
Let's go ahead and put a title in here,
我们叫它Imaginarium
we'll call this Imaginarium.
还要进行segue跳转
Now I want to segue,
按下按钮后 跳转到右边这里
when any of these buttons is pressed to do this,
只要control拖拽就行了
so I'm just going to control, drag,
对这个按钮进行control拖拽 选择push
so let's control, drag this one. Push.
Control, drag this one. Push.
对这个按钮进行control拖拽 选择push
And control, dray this one. Push.
可以看到这三个segue
Now, you see I've got these three segues in here,
点击一个 它就会告诉我
if I click on one, it'll tell me what sent...
什么引发了这个segue跳转
what, what is causing that segue to happen,
很不错的功能
which is kind of a nice feature.
这里的标识符要用什么呢
Now what am I going to use for my identifier for here?
实际上 这里要用点技巧了
Well actually, I'm gonna be a little bit tricky here,
我要用图片名作为标识符
I'm gonna use the name of the photo as the identifier,
然后在prepareForSegue中用它来选取
and then in my prepareForSegue, I will use that to pick
要展示哪幅图片
which of the three photos I'm gonna show.
这是个示例演示
So, you know, it's a demo,
尽量少用代码
so I'm trying to make this as little code as possible,
这就是我的三个segue
so here's my three things,
对应的标识符是这三个图片名
they're going to have these three identifiers,
我需要在这里添加prepareForSegue
and I need to do prepareForSegue in this guy,
我们来做一下
right, so let's go do that.
这样做
Let's do it this way,
转到左边的ViewController
let's go over here to our ViewController.
这些都不需要
We don't need any of this,
这是我们的通用视图控制器
this is our generic view controller, on the side there.
所以只需要实现prepareForSegue
So I only need to implement prepareForSegue,
需要用刚才创建的ImageViewController
and I'm gonna use the ImageViewController that I just created,
因为它是要segue跳转去的对象
because this is the thing I'm going to segue to, alright?
所以只需要写
So all I'm going to do is I'm going to say
if(segue.destinationViewController
if the segue's destinationViewController
isKindOfClass:[ImageViewController class])
is kind of class in ImageViewController, okay,
然后我就知道如何进行segue跳转了
then I know how to segue to that.
还差一个方括号
So, I, oops, one more square bracket there.
只要在这里创建一个局部变量
So I'm just gonna create a local variable here,
ImageViewController *ivc=(ImageViewController *)
ImageViewController ivc equals ImageViewController
segue.destinationViewController
segue dot destinationViewController,
我知道没问题
which I know is okay
因为我在这里做了内省
because I did this introspection right here,
所以我知道这行代码不会出问题
so I know this line is not gonna cause a problem,
然后是ivc.imageURL
and then I'm just gonna say ivc dot imageURL, okay,
还记得吗 它是ImageViewController的公有API
remember this is the public API of our ImageViewController,
这就是prepareForSegue中要做的操作
okay, and that's what we do when prepare for segues,
调用目标视图控制器的公有API
we call public API on the destination view controller.
将它设为NSURL URLWithString
So I'm gonna set that to be NSURL, URLWithString,
我要加一个带格式字符串
and I'm gonna make a string with a format,
我要做的是
and what I'm gonna do is
复制粘贴这里的地址
I'm gonna copy and paste this thing right here,
刚才打开过的苹果网站路径
that I went to, this Apple thing,
我们复制一下
so let's copy that.
粘贴到这里
And paste it in here. Paste.
这里不用photo_1
But instead of just doing photo one here,
而要用segue的标识符
I'm going to use the segue's identifier.
为了方便查看效果
Okay? And just so we can see what's going on,
我还要将这个视图控制器的标题
I'm also gonna set the title of that view controller
设为segue的标识符
to be the segue's identifier, as well,
photo_1 photo_2等
that little photo underbar one, or photo two,
这样就可以在顶部看到是什么图了
just so we can see at the top what it is.
大家都明白在prepareForSegue这里
So everyone understand what I'm doing
我做了什么吗
in prepareForSegue here?
如何为ImageViewController做准备
How I'm preparing my ImageViewController
让它做目标操作
to do what it wants to do? Okay?
我们来看看一切是否正常运行
So, let's see if we got everything working here.
希望我没有落掉什么步骤
Hopefully I didn't forget anything.
试着让应用在设备上运行
Try to get it working on our device here,
出来了
oh, here comes something.
好的 看
Alright, so, look,
初始是横屏模式
it's starting off in the landscape mode,
我可以切换到竖屏模式
I can rotate to either one.
我们来看一下花的图片
So let's try to take a look at the flower.
确实把花的图片显示出来了
Now, it, it did show me the flower,
至少左上角显示出来了
at least the upper corner of it,
但我不能进行滚动缩放 什么都做不了
but I can't scroll around, I can't zoom, I can't do anything,
可以看一下小辣椒图片
I could go look at the peppers.
注意 我的UI有点卡
Notice that my UI is kind of stuck.
点击水母后 我就不能再动了
When I press jellyfish, ah, now I can't,
不能改变主意
like I can't change my mind.
选择小辣椒以后 就不能改了
Once I choose peppers, I can't change my mind.
这是因为执行这个抓取操作时
And that's because I'm blocking that main queue
会阻塞主队列
by doing this fetch. Okay?
我们稍后讲一下如何修复这个问题
So we're gonna see how to fix that a little bit later.
到目前为止都不错
So, this is good, so far,
但如果能看到这朵花
but it'd be a lot nicer
就更好了
if I could take a look at this flower,
滚动查看
right, scroll around and look at it,
下面我们就来实现一下
so let's do that next.
实现方法是添加一个滚动视图
And, we're gonna do that by adding a scroll view.
转到storyboard
So, I'm just gonna go here to my storyboard,
在这里的图像视图控制器中
and here, inside my Image View Controller,
这是我的图像视图控制器
this is my Image View Controller,
这里我要加一个滚动视图
I'm going to add a scroll view,
方法是转到右下角
and we do that just by going down here,
添加对象都是从这里
where we add everything from,
找到滚动视图
and finding a scroll view
在靠近底部的位置 在这
and it's down towards the bottom, oh, there it is.
滚动视图
Okay, scroll view.
将它拖拽出来
I'm just going to pull it out.
让它填满全屏
I'm gonna make it match the whole thing,
选择重置为建议约束
I'm gonna actually do reset to suggested constraints,
我总是希望检查一下
I always like to see
它是否真的选择了较好的约束
if it actually picked good constraints,
这里是的
which it did, okay?
滚动视图会紧贴边缘
It's gonna have that scroll view stick to the edges,
当旋转
so as we rotate
或者在不同大小的视图中查看时
or if we were in a different size viewer, or whatever,
它都会紧贴边缘 我很喜欢
it would stick to those edges, I really like that,
再添加一个连接它的输出口
let's also wire up a outlet for that, an outlet for that.
叫它scrollView
We'll call it scrollView. Alright?
有了它以后就能向滚动视图通信了
So we have that, so now we can talk to the scroll view,
而想要实现它
and all I really need to do to make this work is
不用将imageView添加为视图的子视图
instead of adding the imageView as a subview of the view,
而是将它添加为滚动视图的子视图
I'm gonna add it as a subview of the scroll view.
当然了 这样不能正常运行
But, of course, this will not work.
我来证明一下它不能正常运行
I'll go ahead and prove to you this will not work.
我是故意这样做的
And I'm doing this intentionally,
我花时间这样做
and I'm taking time to do this
是因为大家也会犯这个错误
because you'll make this mistake, as well,
这是个常见错误
a very common mistake.
看看花朵图片 出来了
Just looked at the flower, here's the flower.
不行啊
Oh! It's not working.
它是在滚动视图中
Okay, it's in that scroll view
我把它放进滚动视图的
and I know I put it in a scroll view,
怎么会不能用呢
how come it's not working?
有人想告诉我为什么吗
Anyone want to tell me why?
[学生回答]
Student:[inaudible]
contentSize 没错
ContentSize, exactly.
我们需要设置contentSize
We have to set the contentSize.
现在滚动视图不知道
So right now the scroll view doesn't know
在哪里滚动
where to scroll over, and...
大家可能会问 为什么这里有图片显示
you might ask why is it even showing anything here,
答案是 我认为滚动视图...
and the answer is I think scroll view,
将它添加到storyboard中时
when you add it in a storyboard,
它可能将contentSize设为了其bounds
it might set its contentSize to be its bounds
或者类似的东西
or something like that,
所以这只是默认设置
so it's just some defaulting that's even make it
让我们可以看到里面的内容
so we see anything there.
我们回到这里 解决这个问题
Okay, so let's go back here and fix that.
那我们要在哪里设置contentSize呢
So where do we want to set the contentSize then?
扩大点空间 方便大家看到全部代码
And, let's make it so we can see all this code. All right?
要设置contentSize
The contentSize, for sure we want to set,
只要修改了image 我们就要设置contentSize
anytime we change the image, we want to set the contentSize,
这毫无疑问 我们来做一下
there's no doubt about that, so let's do this,
self.scrollView.contentSize
self dot scrollView dot contentSize,
打错了 是contentSize
oops, size,
=self.image.size
equals self dot image dot size.
这行代码可能会出问题
Okay? Now, this line of code could cause trouble
如果self.image为nil的话
if self dot image is nil,
因为我说过 如果你有一个方法
because I told you that if you have a method,
这只是image的getter
this is just a getter of the image,
返回一个结构体 你将它发给nil
that returns a struct, and you send it to nil,
就会得到未定义的结果
you'll get undefined results.
这很不好
So this is bad.
我们来避免这种情况发生
So let's protect against that,
self.image ?
self dot image, question mark,
然后用size
then we'll use the size,
否则 我们用CGSizeZero 即(0,0)
otherwise, we'll use CGSizeZero, which is 0 by 0.
这样可以正常运行
Okay? Now, this will work,
但实际上 还有一个地方
but there's actually one other place
需要这行代码
that we need to put this.
大家可能会觉得惊讶 就是在setScrollView中
And that, maybe surprisingly, is in setScrollView.
也就是这个输出口的setter
In other words, in the setter for this outlet,
这里的这个scrollView输出口
this scrollView outlet right here,
它只是个输出口
it's just an outlet.
_scrollView=scrollView
We want... equals, scrollView,
要确保两行代码一致
we want to make sure that we do this exact same line of code,
为什么呢
and why is that?
因为这个scrollView属性
Well, the reason for that is this scrollView property
可能会在这个方法执行后被设置
might get set after this happens.
特别是prepareForSegue
Specifically, prepareForSegue, right,
prepareForSegue是在输出口未设好前执行的
prepareForSegu happens before your outlets get set,
明白吗
make sense?
setImage会因为setImageURL而执行
So this setImage is gonna be happening because of this setImageURL
而setImageURL是在prepareForSegue被执行的
which happens in the prepareForSegue
滚动视图这时还没建好
and so the scroll view is not even set up at that time,
所以在这里执行时 它还是nil
so this is gonna be nil, at the time that is executed.
大家明白吗
Okay? Everyone understand that?
不明白吗 明白就点头
No? Nod your head if you understand.
人数不多
Not too many of you.
也许大家需要
Okay, well you might have to think
再思考一下
about that one a little bit, okay?
只要理解 当prepareForSegue为你做准备时
Just understand that your outlets are not send... are not set
你的输出口还没有建好
when prepareForSegue is preparing you, okay?
prepareForSegue中会设置这个imageURL
So prepareForSegue is setting this imageURL,
因而执行这个方法
which is happening this,
执行这行代码
which is causing this,
然后会转到下面这里来
which is going down to here,
试图执行这一行 但它是nil
which is trying to do this, but this is nil,
所以这行什么都不会执行
so this line will do nothing.
因为这里是向nil发送消息
Because we're sending a message to nil here,
所以它什么都不会做
so it just does nothing.
稍后当这个输出口建好之后
So later when this outlet comes along and get set,
这时如果我们有一幅图像
then if we have an image,
要确保设置了contentSize
we want to make sure that we set our contentSize, okay?
大家可以再思考一下
Alright, so, you can cogitate on that.
与此同时 我们运行一下
Meanwhile, let's run this,
希望现在可以正常运行了
and hopefully now it'll work.
查看花朵图像
So we'll look at the flower.
起作用了
And oh it's working!
花朵出来了
Okay. So there's our flower,
但是不太容易看清 因为不能缩放
it's a little hard to see because we can't zoom in.
如果能缩小就好了
Alright? It'd be nice to be able to zoom in on this,
小辣椒图片也是一样 它好看一点
same with the peppers, the peppers, a little nicer to look at,
也不太好看
this, that's not so nice to look at, but,
可以看到小辣椒在这里
there you can look at the peppers over here.
这些图都太大了 显然我们需要缩小
Okay, so these are too big, obviously we want to zoom in,
如何缩小呢
so how are we going to zoom in?
我们来做一下
Let's do that.
实现缩小操作非常简单
Zooming in, really simple,
还记得我说过只要两步吗
remember I said you only need to do two things, okay?
首先是需要设置
One is you got to set
滚动视图的最大最小缩放比例
the scroll view's minimum and maximum zoom scale,
我们让它缩小到...
so we'll let it zoom into...
图像实际大小的20%
let's say 20 percent, of the size of this image, or zoom out.
最大缩放比例设为两倍
And then, we'll have the maximum zoom scale be two times.
图像不允许放大超过两倍
Okay? So, we won't allow the image to get any bigger
最多可以缩小到20%
than twice as big and we'll zoom down to 20 percent.
除此之外 另一个操作是需要
And the other thing we need to do besides setting those is
设置滚动视图的委托
to set the scroll view's delegate
实现另一个方法
and implement that other method.
我要将滚动视图的delegat设为它自己
So I'm gonna set the scroll view's delegate to self.
看到了吗
Okay?
这触发了一个警告
This causes a warning.
看到那个黄色小三角形了吗
You see that yellow triangle?
在我点击它之前
Why do you think there's a warning here
有谁能说说为什么这里会出现一个警告
before I clicked on it, anyone?
请说
Yeah?
[学生回答]
Student:[inaudible]
没错 但是有一个间接的步骤
Yes. So the, that's, yes, but there's an indirect step,
这个警告的意思略有不同
and this warning is actually telling me something slightly different,
是过程中的消息
but it, it's telling me something on the way
还没到你说的那一步
to exactly what you're saying,
我们是要实现viewDidZoom方法
which is we got to implement that viewDidZoom thing.
但这个警告并不是这个意思
But that's not what this warning is warning us about.
这个警告是说
This warning is saying that
你将委托赋给了一个对象
you are assigning this delegate to an object
但它没有实现滚动视图委托协议
that does not implement the scroll view delegate protocol, okay?
不是实现方法
Now that's not implementing the methods,
是声明自己实现了这些方法
that's declaring that it does it.
就是上面这里
That's this up here.
这就是警告的内容
Okay? This is what it's complaining about,
你没有声明你自己
is that you don't declare self,
也就是这个ImageViewController
which is this image controller,
实现委托协议
to implement the delegate protocol, okay?
还记得委托协议吗 有两个步骤
So remember the delegate protocol, there's two things.
首先 声明你实现了
One, they're saying that you do it
然后实现它
and then number two, doing it.
声明的部分
Okay? So it's the saying that you do it
就是警告缺少的内容
that it's complaining about,
现在没有警告了
and now it's not complaining.
即便我并没有真正实现任何一个方法
Even though I don't actually implement any of those methods.
为什么没有警告呢
Okay? Why is that not complaining?
因为那些方法都是可选的
Because they're all optional.
如果其中某个方法是必需的
If any of those methods would required,
这里就会出现警告
then it would be complaining here,
会提示 你没有实现这个必需方法
it would be saying you don't implement this required method.
但因为都是可选的 所以这里没有警告
Okay? But since they're all optional, it doesn't do it.
但并不是真的不需要 因为我们想要实现缩放
But, it's not really optional for us because we want zooming,
但缩放方法本身是可选的
it's only optional because zooming is optional,
我们需要在这里声明滚动视图中要缩放的视图
but we have to specify here the view for zooming in scroll view.
我们需要返回要缩放的目标子视图
Okay? We have to return which of the subviews we want to zoom,
这里只有一个 就是imageView
and we only have one, which is in our imageView.
我们返回它
So we're going to return that
这样当滚动视图中发生缩放时
and it's gonna cause the imageView to be zoomed
imageView就会被缩放
when zooming happens in the scroll view.
如果这里返回nil
If we returned nil here,
那么控制缩放的捏合手势
then that pan, the zooming rather, pinching,
在滚动视图中不会有任何效果
would do nothing in the scroll view.
缩放效果 即修改transform值
Okay? It's only going to zoom, I.E. Change the transform,
只针对这里指定的返回子视图
of whatever subview you specify by returning here, okay?
我们来运行试试
So let's try this.
看看能否缩小
See if we can zoom in.
打开花朵图片
Alright, so we go to the flower.
花朵出来了 试试缩小 可以了
There's our flower, let's try zooming in, indeed we can.
也可以放大
Okay, and zoom out.
我没有设置 所以它不能缩小到
Now, I haven't set it so that it zooms small enough
小于滚动视图的大小
to be smaller than the scroll view,
现在是因为我按住它了
but, because I'm holding it right here,
如果我松手 它就会放大
if I let it go, it zooms out,
如果允许这样缩小
but if I allowed that, then what would happen is
底部就会出现这样的白色边框
you'd have this white border at the bottom.
看到了吗
You see that?
白色边框
That white border?
这是滚动视图的背景色透出来了
That's the background color of the scroll view showing through.
我还可以放大 可以放到很大
Okay? And I can zoom in, I can zoom even in so far
甚至显示得有点像素化了
that it starts to get a little pixelated,
因为我放得太大
because I'm zooming in
超过了图片能够显示的像素
more than the picture even has pixels to show me.
所以可以看到中间这里
So right in the middle there,
出现了阶梯状图像
you can see the little stair step.
明白吗
Okay? Make sense?
可以看看另一幅图 小辣椒图
We can look at another one, the peppers.
小辣椒出来了 缩小
Okay, there's the peppers, let's zoom down. Okay?
明白了吗
Make sense?
进展真不错
So, we're making really good progress here.
还有个问题是 如果点击花朵
One problem though is if I say flowers,
UI又被卡住了 怎么回事
and then oh, again, my UI is blocked, what's going on?
真的要解决这个问题
I really got to fix that.
我们不希望选中一个时 UI被卡住
Okay? We don't want our UI to be blocked when we pick one.
比如说 我选择了水母
For example, if I pick jellyfish, I might,
如果很长时间都不出来
if it's taking a long time,
我可能就改变主意了 想选花朵
I might want to change my mind and then go pick flower.
我希望可以在UI中进行任意操作
Okay? So I want to be able to do stuff in my UI
不因为网络调用而被卡住
without it being blocked by this network call.
我们来修改一下
Okay? So, let's fix that.
方法就是让这里的URL抓取操作
And the way we're gonna do that is by doing that URL fetch,
在另一个线程执行
this one right here, in another thread,
在另一个队列中
okay, on a different queue.
我们要怎么做呢
And, so how are we going to do that?
非常简单
Really, really simply.
只要删掉这行代码
I'm just gonna get rid of this line of code,
把它注释掉
comment it out actually,
写上self startDownloadingImage
and I'm gonna say self startDownloadingImage.
然后实现这个方法
Okay? And then we're gonna implement this method,
startDownloadingImage
startDownloadingImage.
这个方法只需要
Okay? And all this thing needs to do
开始下载
is start the download happening,
会在另一个线程中执行
it's going to happen in another thread,
它会通过完成处理程序进行回调
it's gonna call us back with that completion handler
回调之后
and when it does,
就要执行这行代码
I'm gonna execute this line of code, basically, okay,
这部分会使用URL下载任务
but this part I'm gonna do using the URL download task
幻灯片中见过的
that we saw in the slides. Okay?
我们来讲一下这个startDownloadingImage
So let's, let's talk about this startDownloadingImage
以及这个方法是怎样的
and what this method needs to look like.
首先 我要将image设为nil
The first thing is I'm gonna set image to nil, okay?
要求我下载一幅新图像
I've been asked to start downloading a new image,
在下载时
while it's downloading,
我要清除当前图像视图中的内容
I'm gonna clear whatever's in my image view currently.
所以只要将它清空
Okay? So I'm just gonna blank that out.
所以首先要将image设为nil
So I'm gonna set my image to start off to be nil.
然后 只要有能够尝试的imageURL
And then, as long as I have an imageURL to go try,
我们就会尝试下载
then we'll try doing a download,
和幻灯片中讲到的一样
and as we saw in the slides,
先把这里扩大一点
let's make a lot of space here, oops.
我们要将这个URL做成请求
We need to make this URL request, okay?
叫它request
We'll call it request,
只要用NSURLRequest requestWithURL
and that's just NSURLRequest, requestWithURL,
目标URL是什么呢
and what's the URL we want?
self.imageURL
Self dot imageURL. Okay?
这样就创建了一个获取该imageURL的请求
So this creates a request to go get that imageURL,
现在我们需要创建一个任务
now we have to create a task,
一个后台任务来执行这个请求
a background task to go do that request.
我们用URLSessionConfiguration
So let's do this URLSessionConfiguration thing,
在讲幻灯片时只大概提了一下
which I kind of hand waved in the slides,
configuration配置部分
but the configuration, really,
有三种配置可用
there's three different kinds of configurations you can have,
非常简单
it's pretty simple,
一种是ephemeralSessionConfiguration临时会话配置
one is an ephemeralSessionConfiguration,
如果要下载什么内容
that's just if you're gonna download something
下完就完成了
and you're gonna be done.
这就是我们在做的事情
And that's exactly what we're doing.
还有一个是defaultSessionConfiguration默认会话配置
There's another one which is defaultSessionConfiguration.
它表示你可能在下载多个文件
That means you might be multi, downloading multiple files
或者让这个会话保持活动状态
or otherwise you keeping this session active
执行多项内容 这是默认值
and doing multiple things, but it's just the default,
最后一种非常强大
and the last one, really powerful,
但要理解iOS的多任务才能使用
but we need to understand iOS multitasking to do it
叫做backgroundSessionConfiguration后台会话配置
is backgroundSessionConfiguration.
backgroundSessionConfiguration表示开始下载文件后
A backgroundSessionConfiguration means start downloading this file
即使用户切换到其他应用或应用停止
and even if the user switches to another app or my app dies,
也会继续下载
keep downloading it,
下载完成后 再向我发消息
and when it's done, call me back
如果需要的话 启动应用来处理
and launch my app, if necessary, to handle that.
它是很强大的会话模式
Okay? So it was a very powerful session.
但今天我们只用简单一些的临时会话配置
But today, we're just going to do the simpler ephemeral, okay?
现在创建URLSession
And so now we'll just create the session, URLSession.
创建NSURLSession时
And I'm gonna create this NSURLSession
就使用默认方法
using the default way to do it,
只要指定configuration
which is just by specifying the configuration only.
不使用委托或委托队列
I'm not doing the delegate or delegate queue.
所以回调方法会在另一个队列上
So my callback is going to be on a different queue,
不会在主队列上
not on the main queue, alright?
现在来创建URLSessionDownloadTask
And so now let's create that URLSessionDownloadTask, okay?
这个任务
So this task is going to be the...
会为我们执行下载操作
the task that's gonna do the downloading for us,
只要请求session
and we just asked the session,
请用这个请求为我们创建一个下载任务
please create us a download task with that request,
用这个完成处理程序
with this completion handler? Okay?
把这段代码另起一行
And let's go ahead and put this on the other line
方便大家看清楚
so you can see it.
有一个小技巧 如果你的参数
One little trick, if you have an argument
是像这样的block
that's a block like this, okay?
如果双击它 系统就会自动补全内容
If you double click it, it will put it in there for you.
也就是会自动添加这些内容
Okay? In other words, it'll type all this stuff in.
我不喜欢location这个名字
I don't like this name, location,
换一个更清楚的名字localfile本地文件
just to make it clear, this is local file,
这是一个本地文件的URL
this is an URL of the local file
应用会将URL内容下载至这个文件中
that is downloading this content to this URL to.
所以我要叫它localfile
That's why I like to call that localfile.
这就是这部分要做的代码
And then here's the code that we want to do in here.
完成时会发生什么
And, what happens when it's done?
调用这个完成处理程序时
Okay? When we get this completion handler called.
我们要设置self.image 对吧
Well, we want to set self dot image, okay,
但这里有一件事需要注意
but the only thing here we have to be careful is
那就是 我们不在主队列上
we're not on the main queue,
所以要在另一个队列上执行 来做一下
so we have to do that in the other queue, so let's do this.
首先判断 如果没有错误
If there's no error, first of all,
可以看到 这里有个错误参数error
you can see that there's error argument right here,
如果没有错误...
so I'm gonna say if there's no error,
如果有错误
if there was an error,
你可能要在视图某个位置
you might want to put not found or something
显示未找到等等
in your view somewhere,
但如果没有错误
but, if there's no error,
我要做一件有趣的事情
then I'm gonna do an interesting thing here
大家可能会很惊讶
that you might be like, what,
我会检查判断
which is I'm going to check to see
requestURL和self.imageURL的URL是否相等
if the requestURL's URL is equal to self dot imageURL.
我为什么要这样做呢
Okay. Why would I do that?
打错了 这里是request.URL
Oops, request dot URL.
我为什么要这样做
Why would I do this?
这里我们将request设为了self.imageURL
Why would I check to see if this is, which we set to be this,
为什么还要检查它俩是否相等呢
why would I check to see if this is equal to self dot imageURL,
有人知道吗
anyone have an idea?
[学生回答]
Student: [inaudible]
没错
Absolutely.
防止应用中的某个对象
Okay, in case we, somebody else in the app
修改了这个imageURL
changed the imageURL,
在网络下载的过程中
asked us to display something different,
要求应用显示别的内容
while this was outstanding. Okay?
应用去网上抓取URL内容了 比如要花十分钟
This URL is out fetching, let's take, it takes 10 minutes,
是一个很慢的网站
okay, it really is a slow website out there,
要花十分钟 在这十分钟里
it takes 10 minutes, and in that 10 minutes,
用户点击了其他内容
the user clicks on something else
想让这个视图显示其他内容
and wants this view to display something else.
这个下载任务还要十分钟才能完成
Well, this download task is still gonna
但我们想要忽略它了
complete 10 minutes later, but we want to ignore it,
这个请求
basically, because it's a request
请求的是我们不再需要的内容
for something we're not going to use anymore.
这是在理解多任务处理时
So this is something that would be important
很重要的一点
to understand about multitasking,
那就是 操作花费时间
is that things take time,
当操作完成时
and when things are finished,
要确保当前状态
you have to make sure the state of the world
依旧匹配你所认为的
still matches what you thought it was
其开始时的状态
when you asked it to start.
多任务编程
Okay? Multitasking programming,
多线程编程
multithreaded programming rather, is really,
在这方面可能有些令人费解
can be kind of mind-bending in that way,
但你自己要清楚地思考
but you really have to have the discipline to think, okay,
如果这个操作要花费十分钟
what if this takes 10 minutes,
那我要让它做什么
then what, what do I want this to do?
这是你需要做的事情
Alright? So that's the kind of thing you have to do.
在这里 二者是相同的
So, in this case though, it is the same.
我们用返回的URL数据
So let's go ahead and create a UIImage
来新建一个UIImage
out of the URL data that came back,
所以这里我要创建一个本地UIImage
so I'm gonna create a local UIImage here
我要用UIImage imageWithData
and I'm gonna do that doing UIImage, imageWithData,
这里可以直接用localfile
and this time I can just say the localfile,
抱歉 忘了NSData dataWithContentsOfURL
oops, sorry. Go do NSData dataWithContentsOfURL.
但这里的URL就是这个localfile
But now the URL is this localfile. Okay?
这段代码执行的是本地操作
So this, this right here, is doing locally,
所以不会发生阻塞 而这行代码会
so it's not going to block, like this one did.
这里阻塞 因为它可能是一个http网络URL
This one blocked because this could be a network http URL,
而它是一个本地文件 所以不会发生阻塞
this one, is a local file so it can't block.
注意这里的操作
Okay? Now, notice that I'm doing this.
看起来像是个UIKit调用
It looks like a UIKit call.
是在主队列上的吗
Am I doing this on the main queue?
不是
No.
有人点头 有人摇头
I see nodding heads or shaking heads.
说对了 不是
You're right, no.
这不是在主队列上执行的
This is not happening on the main queue.
而且这样是可以的
And it turns out that that's okay.
UIImage是UIKit类中少数的
UIImage is one of the few UIKit classes
允许不在主队列上执行操作的类之一
that you're allowed to do things to off the main queue.
因为实际上
And that's because this is not actually
这里并不会做任何屏幕操作
gonna do anything on screen,
我只是在这里创建了一个局部变量
I'm just creating a local variable here
解析这个URL 查看对应数据
that is parsing this URL, looking at its data,
为我创建一幅图像
and creating an image for me. Okay?
为了好看清楚一点
Here let's make this a little more readable
把这段代码移到前面
by moving this back.
这里实际上不会涉及UI操作
Okay? So, this is not gonna actually touch the UI,
这时只是创建UIImage对象
I'm just creating the UIImage object at this point,
没问题
that's okay.
但是下一行代码 我要用
But the next line of code I want to do
self.image=image
is self dot image equals image, okay?
现在我想要将我的图像设成这幅图
Now I want to set my image to that.
这行代码要在主队列上执行
This line of code has to happen on the main thread,
看一下在设置图像的方法setImage里
because look at all the UI stuff we're gonna do
我们要做的各种操作
when we do set image,
我们要向滚动视图发送消息
we're gonna be talking to the scroll view,
要适应图像显示大小
we're gonna be doing size fit,
要修改contentSize
we're gonna change the contentSize,
这里可以做各种操作
this can be doing all kinds of stuff,
所以要在主队列上运行
so this has to be on the main thread,
具体实现方法就是用dispatch_async
and so I'm gonna do that with dispatch async.
dispatch_get_main_queue 然后是一个block
Dispatch underbar queue, get main queue, and a block here,
然后把这个调用放到block中
and inside this block, I'm gonna put this call right here.
剪切 粘贴
Cut and paste. Right? Okay?
还有一种方法是
Now another way I could have done this was
self performSelectorOnMainThread:@selector(setImage:)
self performSelectorOnMainThread, at sign selector, setImage
withObject:image waitUntilDone:NO
withObject, the image, waitUntilDone, NO.
这两行代码
Okay, these two lines of code
基本上是完全一样的
are pretty much exactly the same thing.
大家明白了吗
Okay? Everybody understand that?
明白这行代码吗
Okay, everyone understand this line of code?
有问题吗
Question?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
问题是 下载这幅图像之前
Yeah, so the question is before I start downloading this image,
要不要检查一下
wouldn't I want to check to see
是否已经有正在进行的下载任务
if I already have a download going on,
答案是 是的 要检查一下
and the answer is yes you would.
这只是个示例演示 我们就不做了
You know, this is demo, we're not doing it,
但是大家可以这样做
but you would want to do that,
你可能要有一个局部变量
you probably want to have a local variable
是当前下载的URL
which is the URL that you're currently downloading,
甚至要有一个URL数组
maybe even an array of them.
因为用户可能会来回点击
Because the person might click back and forth and back and forth,
这些URL是正在下载的内容
and so these are all the ones I have outstanding,
然后你可能要查找一下
and then you'd want to go and look and see
看是否包含目标对象
if it contains that object,
如果已经有了 就不要再下载了
and if it does, just don't, don't do this.
等它下载完成
Okay? Wait for it to come back.
很好的想法
So that's really good, good point.
这里有一个警告 抱歉 有问题吗
And then I have this warning right here, oh sorry, question?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
好的 问题是 你是说
Yeah, so, the question, so you mean
各种操作对应的队列...
which, where is this queue that all this stuff...
何时开始一个新队列呢
When do we start a actually new queue?
这个队列
Yeah, so that, that queue,
会执行这个完成处理程序
that is going to do this completionHandler, right,
这里的这个completionHandler
this completionHandler right here,
创建它的队列是由会话任务创建的
the queue to create that is created by the session task,
当需要时 它就会创建它
and it creates it when it needs it.
可能就是在
Probably it creates it
调用这个completionHandler前创建的
right before it calls this completionHandler,
但如果你有一个委托
but if you had a delegate
它可能会在开始时就创建它
it might create it right at the beginning
然后用它来调用委托
and use it to call your delegate, right?
在这里 你可能是在需要用它
So in this case, you probably created it
触发这段代码之前创建它的
right before you need it and fired this off.
因为真正的URL下载操作
Because the actual URL download is happening
是在另一个队列中执行的
in yet another queue, right?
URL下载队列
The URL downloading queue,
实际上 可能是在另一个进程中执行的
and, in fact, it could be another process
如果你用了后台会话模式
if you use that background session thing.
这是我想到的
So that's all I think,
但这个队列应该是在
but this queue is probably created
调用这个completionHandler前创建的
right before it calls this handler,
是由URLSession创建的
it's created by the session, URLSession,
在调用这个completionHandler前创建的
right before it calls this handler.
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
不
No.
因为这是完全不同的队列
Because this is totally separate queue,
毫无关联
totally unrelated to it. Okay?
我们只会在这里用到主队列
This is the only time we're touching the main queue,
就是这里
right here, is when we...
即便在这里 这个block会被放到主队列中
and even here, this block gets put in line on the main queue,
而主队列可能在执行别的操作
the main queue might be busy doing other things.
从它的队列中调取别的block
Okay? Pulling other blocks off its queue,
因为这个block排在队列末尾
because this goes at the end of the line.
所以如果有其他block
So if there's other blocks,
会先执行它们
those are going to get executed first
最后才会执行这个block
and then eventually this block will get executed. Okay?
这里有一个警告
So anyway, we have this one warning right here,
为什么会有这个警告呢
why do we have this warning?
因为我们创建了这个task
That's because this task, we created it,
但一直没有向它发送任何消息
but we never sent it a message,
看到了吗 这里提示的是未使用变量task
you see, this says unused variable task,
很好地提醒了我们 要加上task resume
and that's a good reminder for us to say task resume,
如果不加上task resume
because if you don't say task resume,
这个task开始时就会挂起
this task starts out suspended
不会做任何实际操作
and it will never actually do anything,
就待在那等着有人恢复它
just sit there waiting for someone to resume it.
请讲
Yeah?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
问题是 是否有方法可以结束任务
Yeah, so the question is, is there ways to abort tasks,
我再大体讲一下
I'm gonna talk more generically
线程或队列上的block
about blocks on threads, or on queues.
如果一个block离开队列
If a block is taken off a queue,
开始运行 就不能被终止了
it starts to run, it cannot be stopped.
需要它自己停下来
It has to stop itself.
它会意识到
It would have to realize, oh, this no longer makes sense
不用我再做我做的事情了
for me to be doing what I'm doing, okay?
URLSession中有个API是做这个的
There is some API in the URLSession to do things like that,
但我想让大家明白 对于队列上的block
but I want you to understand that for blocks on queues,
一旦它们开始执行 就不能被终止了
once they start, they cannot be stopped,
只能自己停下来
they can only stop themselves.
只能自己退出
They can just exit from themselves
当它们意识到自己已经不被需要的时候
when they realize they're no longer necessary.
我没有时间详细讲URLSession部分了
Okay? I don't have time to get into the URLSession stuff,
这就是你的问题的答案
but that's the answer to your question.
好了 我们来看看运行效果
Okay, so, let's see if, how this works.
希望我没落东西
Hopefully I haven't forgotten anything here.
现在 如果我点击花朵
Okay, so now if I picked flower,
大家已经能看出不同了吧
you can already see its different, okay?
当我点击小辣椒时 立刻就跳转到了这里
When I click peppers, it immediately goes here,
即使这时这里是空的
even though it's blank, okay?
图片稍后才显示出来
And the photo comes in later, okay?
但跳转很快 实际上我还可以返回
But it's immediate and, in fact, I can go back,
我不想要花 我想要小辣椒
flower, nah, I don't want flower, I want peppers,
不要这个 我想要看水母
nah, I want jellyfish.
UI反应迅速
Okay? And, so the UI is taking complete response,
即便我将这些图片下载了很多遍
even though I'm downloading these things multiple times,
在后台下载 且是不必要的
actually, in the background, unnecessarily, but,
我们希望UI响应迅速且灵敏
so this is a way you want your UI to be, very responsive, okay,
用户想要什么
and just things happening, you know,
立即就执行
the instant the user wants them, okay?
但这个UI还有一点不太好
Now, there's one thing that's kind of bad about this UI though
点击这里时
is when I click here,
这里在做的操作没有反馈
there's no feedback that's doing anything here,
看起来就像是 我点击了花朵
this just looks like oh, well, I clicked on flower,
但显示没有花
oh, there must not be a flower, right?
斯坦福的网速太快了 一下就出来了
Stanford's network is so fast, [inaudible] but..
用户可能会觉得没有花 那我换下一幅
he's like oh there's no flower, oh I'll skip it,
没有小辣椒 我换
there's no peppers, I'll...
因为它在做的操作没有反馈
because there's no feedback that it's doing anything.
我们来加一个反馈提示
So let's put some feedback in here that shows something moving
移动标志或者小转轮之类的
or something, you know, a little spinning wheel
告诉用户 我为你做事呢
that shows the user hey I'm doing something for you,
在后台运行着呢 不用担心
in the background, not to worry.
iOS中有一个内置的UIView
And there is a UIView that's built into iOS,
使用它能够轻松地实现这个功能
that's really easy to use for doing exactly that.
回到storyboard这里
So let's go back to our storyboard here.
这是我们的storyboard
So we have our storyboard,
在右边这个视图中
and what I'm gonna do is into this view right here,
我要拖进一个UIActivityIndicator
I'm gonna drag a UIActivityIndicator,
在上面
just towards the top here,
看起来就是个转轮的样子
it even looks like a spinning wheel,
我们要的就是这个小转轮
so this is the little spinning wheel that you're seeing,
我将它拖进这里
so I'm going to drag it in here.
这里正好可以
Now, this is gonna be a good opportunity
讲讲文档大纲
to talk about document outline.
当我把它拖进来时 不错
So when I drag this in, okay, that's great,
看起来做得很好
it seems like I've done a good thing.
我已经把它拖进来了
I've dragged this in here.
但实际上 这样做并不是太好
But actually, I didn't do a very good thing here,
因为这样将它拖拽进来
because dragging that in
实际上让它成为了滚动视图的一个子视图
actually made that a subview of the scroll view.
当你拖进一个视图 放在另一个视图上面
Okay? When you drag a view in, on top of another view,
它就会成为该视图的子视图
it makes a subview of that.
可以在左边的文档大纲中看到
And we can see that over here in the document outline.
这是滚动视图
Here's the scroll view.
看到它缩进了吗
And see how this is indented a little?
代表它是一个子视图
That means it's a subview.
我不想让它成为子视图
Now, I don't want it to be a subview,
我想让这个转轮显示在滚动视图前面
I want this wheel to sit in front of the scroll view, right,
当滚动视图执行操作时 转轮转动
and be spinning whenever the scroll view is doing something
停止操作时 转轮隐藏
and go, and to hide itself when it stops,
不让它成为子视图 方法是选中它
and so I can make this not be subview by picking it up
移动为并列视图
and moving it to be a sibling.
现在的问题是我将它放在了后面
Okay? Now, the problem here is I put it in the back,
排在上面的子视图显示在后面
things at the top of the view, subview are in the back,
所以我可以将它拖到上面这里
so I can just put this up here,
现在转轮在前 滚动视图在后
and now I've got this in front and this in back.
它们是同级并列的
Okay? And they're siblings.
它在前面
So this is in front, okay?
这里还要做一件事
Another thing I want to do here
就是设置它的约束
is set my constraints on this guy,
转到这里
so I'm gonna go here
将它设为水平垂直居中
and I'm gonna set it to be horizontal/vertical centered,
可以检查一下
and we can just make sure
是否设置正确 没问题
that it did the right thing, which it did. Okay?
有些黄线 我们把它弄好
We got a little yellow there, so let's fix that.
选择修复错位 将它放到正中间
Fix misplacement, put it right in the middle, okay?
这样就好了
So we got that.
还有一件事要做
The other thing I want to do is,
我想让这个小转轮变大
I want this little spinning thing, I want it to be large
所以样式这里选择Large White大白样式
so the style I'm gonna use is large white,
但我不希望它是白色的
but I don't want it to be white,
它是在白色背景上的
because it's on a white background.
如果是白色就几乎看不清楚了
So I'm barely gonna be able to see the thing,
我们来修改它的颜色
so let's change the color.
把它的颜色修改为
So let's make the color be,
换成和按钮一样的蓝色
hmm, let's make it be like the blue of the buttons,
蓝色转轮挺好的
okay, that's a pretty good color for it to be.
还要注意这两个Behavior行为选项
Also, notice these behaviors.
Animating动画代表它以动画形式开始
Okay? Animating means this thing starts out animating,
我们想要这种效果 因为当这个视图刚出现时
which I want, because when this view first appears,
我想让它演示动画
I want it to be animating,
因为开始时是在加载页面
because I'm loading from the start.
下面的选项是停止时隐藏
And then here's hides when stopped,
表示当你在代码中停止它时
that says when you stop it in your code,
转轮就会隐藏起来
it's gonna hide it.
这样它就不会不停转动
So it's not gonna stop turning
始终显示在那里 阻塞滚动视图
and then sit there blocking your scroll view,
它自己会隐藏起来
it's going to hide itself.
这是个非常棒的功能
Okay? So that's a really cool feature,
通常都会选择停止时隐藏
you almost always want hides when stopped on there.
可能不需要开始动画
Okay? You may or may not want it to start out animating,
但通常要选择停止时隐藏
but you always want to hide when stopped.
现在我们回到代码这里
Okay? So, now, let's go back to our code, over here,
何时开始和结束它呢
and when do we want to start and stop this thing, okay?
什么时候开始结束比较好呢
When's a good time to start and stop?
比较好的开始时间是
Well, a good time to start it is
开始下载图像时
when we're starting to download an image.
我要用... 对了 在此之前
So I'm gonna say, oh, well first of all,
我们为什么不做个指向它的输出口呢
why don't we make an outlet to it?
回到storyboard
So let's go back to our storyboard,
选择系统编辑器 关闭文档大纲栏
let's get our system editor up here, let's close this,
我们开着文档大纲栏吧
and let's, actually let's leave that open
我要演示一下
because I'll show you,
我说过 从文档大纲中
I promised you that control drag
进行control拖拽很好用
from the document outline would be good
这里就是显示出它好用的地方
and here's an example of when it's really good,
想要从这里进行control拖拽有点困难
because trying to control drag from this might be a little dicey,
但从这里拖拽是很容易的
but over here, it's really easy.
我只要从这里按住control键进行拖拽
So I'm just gonna control, drag from here
拖拽到图像视图控制器 没选中
into my image view controller, oops, missed it.
这里
Right there.
我们叫它spinner
Okay? And we'll call it spinner.
可以看到spinner是UIActivityIndicator类型
So there's a spinner, see it's a UIActivityIndicator.
现在回到这里 选择视图控制器
Alright so now let's go back to here, and our view controller,
尽可能扩大显示宽度
make it as wide as possible.
现在有了这个self.spinner 在这里
Okay, so now I have this self dot spinner up here.
我要告诉它
And now I'm going to tell it,
当我开始下载图像的时候
when I start downloading an image,
self.spinner startAnimating
self dot spinner startAnimating.
这就是要发送给转轮的方法
Okay? So that's the method that you send to a spinner
告诉它开始动画
to tell it to start animating,
如果它是隐藏的 设置了动画时不隐藏
and if it's hidden and you have that hides when animated,
它就会显示出来 开始转动
it'll unhide itself and start spinning.
如果它不是隐藏状态 就会直接开始转动
If it's not hidden, it'll just start spinning.
那么何时停止它动画比较好呢
Now when's a good time to stop it from animating?
最合适的时间
Well, the best part, time,
大概就是当有人设置图像的时候
is probably when someone sets an image.
因为如果这里设置了一幅图像
Okay? Because if an image gets set in here,
那我们基本可以确定设置好了
then we can pretty much be assured that we're setting,
操作完成了 所以就要停止转轮动画了
that we're done, so we'll stop animating then.
所以无论这个setImage的发生
Okay? So whether this setImage happens
是因为下载操作完成了
because that start downloading thing finally finishes,
还是因为有人厌烦了
or because someone gets tired of it
将它设为了某个本地图像
and sets it to some image that's a local image,
这两种情况 我们都要停止转轮
either way, boom, we're gonna stop doing that spinner.
我们来看一下
Okay? So let's take a look at that.
选择花朵
Alright, so we do the flower,
看到转轮了吗
and see we got the spinner,
正在转动 很好
that is spinning, which is nice,
告诉我们有操作正在执行
it's telling us that something's happening,
我们依旧可以中断它
and we can still interrupt it, go back,
转轮的各种操作
it's not blocked, this is not blocking the main thread
不会阻塞主线程
in any way to do that spinner, okay?
但是它能给用户很好的反馈
But it gives the user some nice feedback
告诉用户 我在干活呢
that hey I'm working on something.
有问题吗
Okay? Question?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
好问题
Great question.
问题是 这个URL的使用有效期是多少
So the question is what is the lifetime of this URL.
在这里的completionHandler中
In my completionHandler, right here,
这个localfile的使用有效期是多少
what is the lifetime of this localfile?
答案是只能用于这个block的有效期范围
And the answer is only for the lifetime of this block.
一旦这个block停止执行
Okay? So, as soon as this block stops executing,
那个文件就会被删掉
that file will be deleted.
所以如果你想保存它 就得复制一下
So if you want to keep it, you got to copy it.
复制文件的方法
Okay? And you copy files, by the way,
复制URL要用NSFileManager
copy URLs using NSFileManager.
下周讲持久化时
Okay? We'll probably talk
我们可能会
about NSFileManager briefly next week
快速讲一下NSFileManager
when we talk about persistence,
但它就是复制文件的方法 用API
but that's how you copy files, they are API
从URL复制到URL 就可以复制了
and they're copy from URL to URL and you can copy it away,
很好的想法
but that's a very good point.
这是一个临时文件 只用于这个block
This is a temporary file, only here, you know, for this block.
这个block没有了 文件也就无法继续使用了
And once this block is gone, you're done.
还有一点我要快速讲一下
Okay? The other thing I'm gonna say, really briefly,
我也不知道幻灯片中是否能讲到
I don't know if we'll get to this in slides,
做多任务处理时 我可能会要求大家
when we do multitasking, I'm probably gonna ask you
在这里使用backgroundSessionConfiguration
to use a backgroundSessionConfiguration here
而不是临时会话配置 在这个配置模式下
instead of ephemeral, which is this one where...
即便应用未运行
even if your app's not running,
它也会继续下载目标内容
it will keep downloading that thing,
完成后再调回你的应用
and then eventually call your app back,
想要理解它 需要知道多任务执行的工作原理
but to know that you have to know how the multitasking works.
当这样做时 你需要...
When you do that, you will have to have,
当使用sessionWithConfiguration时
when you do the sessionWithConfiguration,
抱歉 这里补上
sorry, let's do something here.
你需要使用带有委托delegate的
You will have to use the version of this
sessionWithConfiguration方法
that has a delegate, okay?
因为后台会话配置模式
Because the background session one,
需要使用委托
you got to use the delegate,
不能用完成处理程序
you can't use the completion handler.
加上委托就可以了
Okay? Just putting that out there.
我们再讲到这时 我会提醒大家
I'll remind you when we get back to that, but,
但要知道后台模式要使用委托
got to use the delegate for that.
但临时会话配置模式可以使用这个完成处理程序
But for ephemeral, we can use this nice handler.
我们就不讲表视图了
Okay. So, we are not going to start on table view
下次课再讲 我们来看看最后一张幻灯片
until next time, but let me, this last slide here.
说说后面要讲的内容
Talk about what's coming up.
周三的时候 这里写的是更多表视图内容
So on Wednesday it says more table view,
我们会从头开始讲
but we'll, we'll do all the table view.
我还会讲iPad
I'm also gonna do iPad.
专门用于iPad的UI内容
Okay? Talk about the special UI idioms that are on the iPad.
作业呢 我说了
Your homework, as I said,
今天不留作业
there's no homework assigned today,
所以大家两天不用做作业了 太好了
so you get two days off on homework, good job,
周三会布置一个新作业
and then Wednesday you'll have a whole new assignment
完成期限一星期
that will be due a week later,
周五有课外辅导
and Friday, we do have section,
会开始的早一点
it's actually gonna be a little bit early,
时间长一些
and last a little longer,
90分钟的课外辅导 而不是50分钟了
it's like a 90 minutes instead of a 50-minute section,
斯坦福的同学记得查看Piazza的通知
so watch Piazza for that Stanford people.
iTunes U上没有
It won't be on iTunes U.
下周我们会讲Core Data
And then next week we're gonna talk about core data
大体讲一下持久性
and persistence in general,
如何让内容留在手机上
how do we make things stay on the phone,
将它们转为数据库
and how do we turn them into a database
进行检索等操作
so we can search for things and stuff like that?
这就是下面要讲的内容
Okay? So that's what's coming up.
谢谢大家 有问题就过来找我吧
Thank you all and I'll be here if you have questions.
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.